<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A moste sure and strong defence of the baptisme of children, against [the] pestiferous secte of the Anabaptystes. set furthe by that famouse clerke, Henry Bullynger: &amp; nowe translated out of Laten into Englysh by Ihon Veron Senonoys</title>
            <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17192</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109521</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845168</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845168</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10054</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17192)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10054)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 184:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A moste sure and strong defence of the baptisme of children, against [the] pestiferous secte of the Anabaptystes. set furthe by that famouse clerke, Henry Bullynger: &amp; nowe translated out of Laten into Englysh by Ihon Veron Senonoys</title>
                  <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
                  <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ihon Oswen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at Worcester :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno .Do .1551]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10054:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10054:1"/>
            <p>¶ A moſte ſure and ſtrong defence of the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of children, againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peſtiferous ſecte of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptyſtes, ſet furthe by that famouſe Clerke, Hen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry Bullynger: &amp; nowe tranſlated out of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into Englyſh by Ihon Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron Seno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noys.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Geneſis. xvij. chap.</bibl>
               <p>I wyl be thy god, and the god of thy ſede after thee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Thou ſhalt reade the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes of thys boke, in the ii. pagyne after this.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:10054:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10054:2"/>
            <head>¶The contentes of thys boke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>i That rebaptizatyon or baptizing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne is not of god, &amp; that there is but one baptyſme.</item>
               <item>ii That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is of god</item>
               <item>iii That the baptyſme of children hath continued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Chriſt euer ſens the tymes of the Apoſtles.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>To the reader.</p>
            <p>I haue, good chriſtian reader, alredy proued and ſet furth theſe artycles that folow, agaynſt theſe erroneous dyuels the Anabaptiſtes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>i The ſpiryt, which repugneth againſt the ſpiryt, which ſpeketh in the holy ſcriptures, is not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of truth but of the deuyl, the father of liyng.</item>
               <item>ii Of the ſimplicyte and lernyng, that ought to be in godly preachers.</item>
               <item>iii Of the vocatyon and callynge vnto the miniſtery &amp; offyce of preachinge againſt them that thruſt them ſelues vnto it, beyng not called.</item>
               <item>iiii Of the vnitie of the church, agaynſte the ſectes of heretikes.</item>
               <item>v That Chriſt dyd not ſuffer onely for originall ſynne.</item>
               <item>vi That a ſynner is receyued to grace as often as he repenteth, and that no
<pb facs="tcp:10054:3"/> man is without ſynne.</item>
               <item>vii That ſaluation &amp; ryghteouſnes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not of our works, but of faith</item>
               <item>viii That the ſoules, which are departed from the bodye, doo not ſlepe but lyue in Chriſt.</item>
               <item>ix That a chriſtian may execute the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce of a magyſtrate.</item>
               <item>x That a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magiſtrate is not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly profytable, but alſo moſt neceſſary to a chriſtian commune weale.</item>
               <item>xi That we ought to be obedient vnto magiſtrates.</item>
               <item>xii That it is not lawful to reſiſt the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrates. which thinges if thou doſt reade dilygently, I truſt thou ſhalte be well enarmed againſt this peſtife<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rous ſecte. Beware of them, for they are worſe then all other herytyques haue bene, yea, they are renewers of all olde hereſyes. So fare ye well.</item>
               <item>And praye to god that all erroneous ſectes beyng vanquyſſhed, his glory may floryſh for euer and euer. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10054:3"/>
            <head>¶ To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right worſhipfull Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Thomas Fletwod, Comptroller of the Kinges Maieſties Minte, in South<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warke, Ihon Heron wyſſheth peace of conſcyence, and encreaſe of dyuyne knowledge and vnderſtandynge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god the father, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not for naughte,<note place="margin">Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother of al errours</note> ryght worſhipfull Syr, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of al men, ignoraunce hath bene compted the mother of all errours. Whiche thynge too be moſt true, we do nowe at this preſence, plainely perceyue and ſe. By godly lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, the erroneous ſecte of the papiſtes is in a maner proflygated and ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, ſo that the chief maynteyners of it are cleane aſhamed of theyr olde occupa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon, I meane,<note place="margin">What godly lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning doth.</note> of theyr Idolatry and ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perſtition. But godly learning was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſoo diligente, in purgynge the fielde of the goſpell from the rubbiſſhes of An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tichriſtes kyngdome,<note place="margin">What ſtubburne ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth.</note> as ſtubburne igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunce is now buſy in ſowynge it ouer, wyth cockle and darnill, wyth tares, and moſt peſtiferous poyſon, whych they do
<pb facs="tcp:10054:4"/> ſo ouer laye wyth ſuger and honye, that is to ſay, wyth paynted and coloured hy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pocriſie, blandiloquence and flatterye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man at the fyrſt ſyght, would embrace thys errour and hereſy, for a moſt whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctryne, and vnfayned relygyon. But if he, puttynge on the ſpectacles of goddes worde, wyll loke more narowly vpon it, he ſhall eſpye ſuche a blyndnes and ignoraunce in theyr procedynges &amp; doctryne, that by good ryght, he myght meruayle, that the very infantes do not now, in thys floriſſhyng tyme of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell, perceyue and ſmell oute thys deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhe hereſie. For who would not ſaye that thys commeth of deuilyſſhe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce (onles he be blynder then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes it ſelfe, that they ſo ſhamefully deny the baptiſme of yong infantes and chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren?<note place="margin">What is to denye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of infants</note> Is not thys too put oure chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, from that euerlaſtyng couenaunte which our lorde god dyd make wyth A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, and in hym, with all vs that be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue? I wyll (ſayth the lorde) be thy god and the god of thy ſede after the.<note place="margin">Gene. xvii chapi.</note> Why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che promyſe Abraham beleued, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore when he came home, he did both cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumciſe hym ſelfe, &amp; al the male chyldren
<pb facs="tcp:10054:4"/> that were in his houſe. For whye? Cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was the ſeale of the people of god, whych by the commaundement of god was miniſtred vnto all them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were comprehended in the Lordes couenaunt In ſtede wherof baptiſme hath bene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in the newe Teſtamente. as the Apoſtle ſayncte Paule. Colloſſ .ij. Chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, Doth playnly teſtifie.<note place="margin">Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion inſted of baptiſm</note> Syth therfore that chyldren were circumcyſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old Teſtament, and long after inſtructed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of the lawe: it foloweth, &amp; that by good conſequence, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptyſme oughte to be myniſtred vnto our yonge infantes, whom we are bound afterwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des to bryng vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth, and true doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne. This argumente al the rablement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Anabaptiſtes, is not able to diſſolue Suffer not therfore, O good chriſtyans, ſuffer not your ſelues too be ſeduced by theſe ſmatteryng Anabaptiſtes, whyche vnderſtande not the letter of the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, wherin (I meane, in the bare letter) they do truſte moſte. And no maruayle thereof: For they are moſte ſhamefullye ignoraunce in all thoſe thynges, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſerue for to expounde and vnderſtand the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. They knowe not the phraſes of the
<pb facs="tcp:10054:5"/> ſcriptures.<note place="margin">
                  <p>The Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce in thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges that ſerue for to expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and vnder ſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>The chyef cauſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Anabaptiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes blynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>roure.</p>
                  <p>Nouatus aucthor of rebaptiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>How ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny wayes this word baptiſm is taken in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente.</p>
               </note> They do not obſerue &amp; mark how many wayes one thing is taken in the ſcriptures and worde of God. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che truely to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyef cauſe of theyr blind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and errour. For yf they had marked howe many wayes in the ſcryptures of the newe Teſtamente, thys worde bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſme is taken, they had neuer renewed the olde condempned hereſye of Noua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, touchyng thys folyſh Anabaptiſme that is to ſaye, rebaptyzaty on or bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zyng agayn. For baptyſme is not alwai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es taken for that outwarde ſygne &amp; ſeale of the people of God, whyche is an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward waſſhyng of water, done and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſtred in the name of the father, of the ſonne, and of the holy ghoſt, wherby we are initiated into a true fayth, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencye of lyfe: whych kynd of baptiſme Ihon and the Apoſtles did mynyſter, &amp; nowe in the churche of Chriſte, is by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adminiſtred, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be appoynted therto: but often tymes it is taken for the doctryne as Mathewe .xxi. Chapter, and Actes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xix. Whych place the Anabaptiſtes do al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege to mayntayne their erroure in thys point. Otherwhiles this word baptiſme ſignyfieth death or matyrdome, as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew
<pb facs="tcp:10054:5"/>
.xx. Chapter. Where Chriſt anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to the ſonnes of Zebede, after thys maner: Can ye drinke the cuppe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhal drinke? and be baptized with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme that I ſhall be baptyzed wyth? there the blynde may ſe, that he did meane his paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion that he ſhould ſuffer. It betokeneth alſo the inward illumynatyon of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite of God, wherby the heartes of the faythfull are illumynated &amp; drawen, as Actes .i. Chapter. Ye ſhal be baptyzed wyth the holy ghoſt after theſe few day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Nowe as they are deceyued in thys thyng by ignoraunce and lacke of know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, ſo are they in all the other poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. But now that the ignoraunt &amp; ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple myght haue an wholſom Antidotus and conterpoyſon agaynſt this peſtilent erroure, eſpecially in thys point of rebap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyzatyon, and baptyſme of chyldren: I haue here tranſlated thre moſt fruyctfull Dialogues vpon thys matter, out of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into Englyſſhe: whyche, yf they be dylygentlye peruſed, maye enarme and fence the reader, agaynſte all the obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyons that can be made and inuented by theſe phantaſtycall and madde braynes. And becauſe that your worſhypfull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſhyp
<pb facs="tcp:10054:6"/> hath bene alwayes earneſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defence of the truth, bearyng a ſinguler affectyon and mynd, towardes all them that are ſtudyous to ſet furth the glorye of god, which godly affection and mynd ye haue many times (as I haue bene by credible perſons enfourmed) declared in your communycatyon, towardes me: I could do no leſſe of duty, but to dedicate thys lytle laboure of myne vnto you, in token of gratitude and thankefulneſſe, ſyth that none otherwyſe, I am able to deſerue or recompence that beneuolente hearte of yours, towardes mee. God of his mercy, vouchſafe with his holy ſpirit ſo to rule and guyde your maſterſhip with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhipfull gentlewoman youre wyfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whatſoeuer yee ſhal do, or thinke in al your affayres, maye be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of god, &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of of your ſoule. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:10054:6"/>
            <head>¶ Thre moſte frutefull Dialo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, treatynge vpon the baptiſme of chyldren, very neceſſary to be red of all Chryſtyans, in theſe moſte paryllouſe tymes. ¶ Symon the Anabaptiſt, Ioiada the true Chriſtyan. ¶ That rebaptizatyon or baptyzyng agayne, is not of god: and that there is but one baptyſme.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Symon.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue taryed here for the, more than an hole houre, Ioiada, I was almoſt per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwaded, I dyd almoſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou durſt not come becauſe that thou haddeſte lyttle truſte and confydence in the other articles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioiada.</speaker>
               <p>There is no artycle, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am ſoo ſure of: it is ſo farre, that I ſhould be afrayde to ſpeake of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Simon.</speaker>
               <p>But I wil proue that rebaptyzation is of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioiada.</speaker>
               <p>By what ſcriptures?<note place="margin">Actes. xix. chapi.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Symon.</speaker>
               <p>By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xix chapter of the Actes, where it is expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſet furthe, that the .xii. men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had bene baptyzed by Ihon, or in the baptiſme of Ihon, were baptyzed agayne by Paule in the name of Chriſte. If it was lawfull after the baptiſme of Ihon, to receyue the baptyſme of Chriſte, why ſhoulde it
<pb facs="tcp:10054:7"/> not be more lawfull, that the baptyſme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Biſſhop of Rome, ſhould giue place vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of Chriſt? For as thoſe men of Epheſus, had bene ignorauntlye and vnwyttingly baptized with the bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſme of Ihon, and agayne were bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by Paul: In like maner, we were ig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norauntly baptized with the baptiſme of the Buſſhop of Rome: Ergo, we maye lawfully be baptyzed agayne, wyth the baptiſme of Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioiada.</speaker>
               <p>As manye wordes as thou haſt ſpoken, ſo many er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rours haſt thou vomyted and ſpued out Fyrſte, thou ſayeſt that thoſe men of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus wer twiſe baptized, which thing thou canſt not proue,<note place="margin">Ac. xix. cha Baptiſme is not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for water, but for the doctryne.</note> for the baptiſme of Ihon, ought not here to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but for the doctryne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Symon.</speaker>
               <p>Thys is the onely refuge that ye flee to, when ye be ouercomen by the truthe. But ye can not proue nor ſtrengthen theſe your ſayinges w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripturs, nor by any truth</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioiada.</speaker>
               <p>But I wil proue vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is not alwaies take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waſſhing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is done in the water,<note place="margin">Ihon. i. &amp; iii. chapter Mat. xxi. chapter.</note> but rather for the doctryne. Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .i. &amp; .iii. chap. And of thys thing, there be moſt ſure tokens, ſignes, notes, as Mat. xxi. chap. where Chriſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:10054:7"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phariſes whether the baptiſme of Ihon was of god, or of men,<note place="margin">Baptiſme is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine for as the water doth waſh away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trew doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine doth clenſe the ſoul fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all errours &amp; ſuperſtyty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on. Act. xii. cha Appollo.</note> &amp; ſithens y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was of god, why dyd they not credite &amp; beleue him, vnderſtanding by baptiſm (as it moſt manyfeſtly appeareth) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne or teſtimony, which they ought to haue beleued,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Simon.</speaker>
               <p>Well, go to, put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this place it is taken for the doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine: yet notwithſtandinge, it foloweth not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Actes of the apoſtles, it ſhuld be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for doctrine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioiada.</speaker>
               <p>In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mean ſeaſon, ye were to much ouerſene in this thing, &amp; ouer blinded, ſaying moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we did affirme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any truthe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme is often times taken for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine. But go to, we wil alſo proue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme is taken in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Acts, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctryne. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xii. of Actes, Luke ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a certain Iue called Apollo, being an eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; taught in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde, did come to Epheſus, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did teache dilygently thoſe thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes, knowing onely the baptiſme of Ihon. Here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry blind may ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Luke did ſpeake, not of the water, but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctryne. The ſame Apollos did teache and inſtruct thoſe. xii men in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of the lord. who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afterwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, Paul doth aſke, whether after that
<pb facs="tcp:10054:8"/> they had beleued &amp; giuen credit vnto the doctrine,<note place="margin">What is to receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt</note> they had bene pacified in theyr hertes &amp; conſciences, by the holy ghoſt. (Here it is to be noted, that faithe is not taken for that heauenlye gyft,<note place="margin">Faythe is here taken for the doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne of fayth.</note> that illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynateth the hearte inwardlye, but for the doctryne of faythe, whyche one man dothe receyue of an other by hearynge) But they dyd ſoo aunſwere, that Paule myght eaſely gather by theyr aunſwere that they knew not what the peace of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſciences, nor what the holye ghoſt was. He marueylyng therefore,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In quid ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiati fuiſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> This word to initiate, whych we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to vſe in thys place, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fieth to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe, or gyue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ani kind of relygyon, ſcience or knowlege.</note> what maner of doctryne thys was, that had not ſet furth vnto them, ſo neceſſary and princi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pall poyntes, dyd aſke them wheruntoo they were baptyzed, not wherin: For he knewe ryght well that men are baptized in water. But he aſketh whervnto they were baptyzed, that is too ſaye, initiated and taughte, what at lengthe was the marke that they dyd ſhoote at, fithens y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they knewe not yet the holy goſt? They made hym anſwere that they were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, that is to ſaye, initiated in the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of Ihon. The Apoſtle dyd vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande and perceyue that they were not yet ryght well taught and inſtructed in
<pb facs="tcp:10054:8"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctryne of Ihon. He begynneth ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, and wyth expreſſe wordes ſetteth furth the doctryne of Ihon. Which wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, if they were well weyghed and pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dered, they make altogether againſt you For thus are the wordes of Paul: <hi>Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes baptiſauit baptiſmo poenitentiae:</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath baptized w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the baptiſm of repentaunce. What meane theſe words,<note place="margin">What is to baptyſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentaunce</note> he hath baptized with the baptiſme of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentaunce, but that Ihon did preache re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentaunce? or did teache how we ought to repent, that will be initiated in Chriſt or receyue the fyrſt inſtructyon in the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligyon of Chriſte? Afterwardes he dyd ſpeake of hym that ſhuld come after him that they might beleue in hym, that is to ſay, in Ieſus Chriſte. Out of the whych fayth and beleife, peace doth ſpryng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde and conſcyence of man. Rom. v.<note place="margin">Ro. v chap</note> chap. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had vnderſtanded that they dyd receyue the baptiſme of water in the name of Ieſus. The wordes that folowe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> impoſityon of handes, make me to expound thys laſt, of the baptiſme of water. As I thynke now, I haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyciently proued, that this place helpeth nothing the Anabaptiſtes: for they, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10054:9"/> mentyon is made of, in the .xix. chap. of Acts, were not baptized againe, but bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyzed once for all, and twyſe inſtructed and taught.<note place="margin">Whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of Ihon, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of Chriſte, be all one.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Symon.</speaker>
               <p>By thys it ſhoulde folowe, that the baptyſme of Ihon, and the baptyſme of Chriſte is all one, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is noo dyfference betwene them.</p>
               <p>Thys can not be, for the doctrine of Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd differre from the doctryne of Chriſt</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioiada.</speaker>
               <p>In this thing ye are greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, for the doctrine of Ihon, and the doctryne of Chriſte, are all one, and their baptiſme all one (Here I do ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of water) and by thys we doo gather and conclude truly, that theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Epheſus were not baptyzed with the baptyſme of Ihon, (I ſpeake of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) for if they had bene baptized wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of Ihon, it had not bene neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and nedefull, that Paule ſhould had baptized them againe in the baptiſme of Chriſte, for bothe theyr doctryne &amp; their baptiſme are all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Symon.</speaker>
               <p>If the doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne of Ihon, &amp; the doctryne of Chrſte were all one, why dyd Luke wryte that Apollo was taught onely in the doctrine or baptyſme of Ihon, and that therefore Priſcilla and Aquilla, dyd take him vnto
<pb facs="tcp:10054:9"/> them, and did teache him more exactly in the way of the lorde.<note place="margin">What is ment by this, that Appollo was taught more exact<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly.</note> If the doctryne of Ihon, and the doctrine of Chriſt were al one, what did nede to teach him more ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>actly? for he that did know the doctryne of Ihon, did alſo knowe the doctryne of Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Luke ſayth, that they did expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto hym more exactly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of the Lorde. The doctryne was all one: but in Apollo there wanted ſomewhat, which knew not all thinges exactly and perfectly. For theſe .xii. do ſaye alſo, that they were taught and inſtructed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme of Ihon, whoſe doctryne for all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they vnderſtode not perfectly, although they were inſtructed in the doctryne of Ihon, yet notwythſtandynge are they taught more exactly by Paul.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>But Paul ſayth not that the doctrine is all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>Thou doſt euery foote bring darkenes into the manifeſt lyght. Tel me, I pray the, which is the ſumme of Chriſtes doctrine, and of the apoſtles?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>And I do aſke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whether Paul in the .xix. chapter of the Actes, did teach that Ihons and Chriſtes doctryne were all one?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>To that wyll I anſwere after that I haue herd of the, whych is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10054:10"/> ſumme of Chriſtes doctrine, &amp; of hys A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.<note place="margin">Note the obſtnacye of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>I will not giue the ouer hand, but perſyſt and abyde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of Luke, which are written, Act. xix chap</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>Thou doſt perſiſte and abide in thy contention and obſtinacie. And this are ye wont to do, eyther when ye haue nothyng to anſweare, and when ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue that ye are ouercommen with the truthe. Go to, I will declare what is the ſumme of the doctrine of Chriſt,<note place="margin">The ſume of the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of Chriſt, and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. Marke. i. Chapter. Math. iiii. Chapter.</note> and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles. Mark. i. chap. It is written af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter this maner: Ieſus came too Galilee, preachyng the goſpell of the kyngdome of god, and ſaying. The time is fulfilled and the kyngdome of god is at hand, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ye, and beleue the goſpel. Mat. iiii. chap. Ieſus departed into Galilee, &amp; did begin to preache and ſay: Repent ye the kingdom of heauen is at hand. Chryſte doth alſo ſende his Apoſtles, ſayinge: As my father hath ſende me, ſoo I do ſend you,<note place="margin">Ihon xx. Chaptre.</note> Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xx. chapter. But the father did ſende Chriſt to preache repentaunce and forgiueneſſe of ſynnes ergo, Chriſte ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his Apoſtles too preache the ſame.<note place="margin">Luke xxiiii. Chapter.</note> This is manyfeſt and playn by the .xxiiii of Luke, and laſte of Marke. So it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:10054:10"/> Chriſt to ſuffer, and to riſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death vpon the thyrd day, and that repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and remiſſion of ſinnes ſhoulde be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched emong all nations in his name, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at Ieruſalem, and ye ſhal be wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſes of theſe thinges.<note place="margin">Actes .ii. iii. Chap.</note> The boke of the Actes doth teſtifie, that the Apoſtles did preache the ſame .ii. iii. chap. Haſte thou any thing againſt ſo manifeſt ſcripturs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>Nothing:<note place="margin">The doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of Chriſt and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of Ihon be all one.</note> But now I aſke the whether the doctryne of Ihon, and the doctrine of Chriſte be all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>I doo proue and conclude by the places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alledged, that it is all one. It is ſayd that the fame of the doctrine of Chriſt &amp; of the Apoſtles, is comprehended in this one thing, that men ſhuld repent, know the kingdome of god to be at hand, and beleue in Ieſus Chriſt. Doſt thou grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t theſe thinges?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>What the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI</speaker>
               <p>Ihon did teache y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſelfe ſame thing: ergo, their doctrine was al one, I proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt propoſityo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third of Mathew: Ihon baptiſt did preache in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſart of Iury, &amp; did ſay: Repent ye, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of god is at hande. In like maner, Luke .i.<note place="margin">Luk. i. cha. Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. and iij. chapter</note> chapter And thou chylde. &amp;c. It is manifeſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt and thyrd of Ihon, that Ihon bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſte
<pb facs="tcp:10054:11"/> did preache the Goſpell, Actes .xix. (Whych place we haue treated vpon al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>redy) he preacheth the ſame, as we maye gather by the wordes of Paule. For he ſpeaketh there after thys maner: Ihon did preache the baptiſme of repentaunce ſpeaking of Ieſus Chriſt, in whom they ſhould beleue. Here I do beſeche the to confeſſe and tell plainely, whether theſe thinges do not ſufficientlye proue that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the doctrine of Chriſt be all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
               <p>What doſt thou ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther &amp; conclude therupon.<note place="margin">The Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptyſtes do teche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they can not proue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>That ye Anabaptiſtes are agayn ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and that ye haue taught that thing whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ye could not proue by the ſcriptures and yet for all that, ye are ſo obſtacle and ſtubburne, that ye wyll in no wyſe gyue place vnto the truth. Who woulde haue beleued the to be ſo ſtiffe necked, that I ſhould be fayne to dryue the to it wyth the ſcripturs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>What make theſe thinges to the baptizing agayn?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Very muche. for if the doctryne of Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the doctrine of Chriſt be al one, their baptiſme alſoo is all one.<note place="margin">There is no exaum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tizinge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</note> Ergo, ye haue no example at all of your rebaptizatyon or baptyzing gayne. Alſo they, whome
<pb facs="tcp:10054:11"/> mentyon is made of Actes .xix. Chapter could not haue bene baptyzed wyth the baptiſme of Ihon. that is done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and againe be rebaptized by Paule. For ſo they ſhoulde had bene twiſe bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tized with one baptiſm of water, and the one ſhould had aboliſſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, which thing can not be done by no mean. For theyr baptiſme is all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt ryghte well, yf there were onelye one baptiſme.<note place="margin">
                     <p>There is onely one baptyſme which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyde.</p>
                     <p>The doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is more excel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lente then baptiſme.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>Ye do not onely deuide the churche, but alſo baptyſme. I do bring againſt the, the wordes of Paul which ſaith: Chryſt hath ſent me, not to baptyſe, but to preache y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel. Now I do aſke the whether of theſe two is more excellent, the doctryne of the Goſpell, or the baptyſme?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
               <p>The doctryne is more excellente then baptiſme, for bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme, is annexed and ioyned, to the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
               <p>If Chriſte and Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do agre in the doctryne, it foloweth that they did alſo conſent and agre in the bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſme, ergo, theyr baptyſme is all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>It can not be alone, for the Apoſtles and Chriſte dydde baptyſe in the name of Ieſus, alſoo in the name of the father, of the ſonne, and of the holye
<pb facs="tcp:10054:12"/> ghoſt, Ihon dyd not ſo: Ergo, it can not be all one baptyſme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt hym ſelfe dyd not baptyſe, but hys Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles in hys name.<note place="margin">Ihon .iiii. Chapter. Ihon .i. Chapter. Marke .i. Chapter. Iuke .iii. Chapter. Ihon and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dyd baptiſe in the name of Ieſus.</note> Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .iiij. Cha. Where as thou ſayeſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ihon dyd not baptyſe in the name Ieſus, thou doſte greatlye erre. For Ihon .i. Chapter. Mar. i. chap alſo, Iuke the thyrd Chapter, it is moſt manyfeſt and playne by his own words that Ihon dydde baptyſe in Ieſus. For there he doth expound his baptyſme, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge, I doo baptyſe wyth water, but he that ſhall come after mee, wyll baptyſe you wyth the holye ghoſte. What other thing is thys, but that I do prepare you to Chriſte, whyche ſhall make you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte. Is not thys to baptiſe in the name of Ieſus? In what, I praye the, dyd the apoſtles baptyſe, but in the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus?<note place="margin">Actes .ii. Chapter.</note> Actes .ii. Chap. Se nowe what thou haſt wonne, truely none other thing, but that with thine own wordes, thou haſte confyrmed and proued, that theyr bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>Yet he dyd not baptyſe in the name of the father, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne, and the holye ghoſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Ihon did not know Chriſt to be one god with the father, &amp; the holy goſt.
<pb facs="tcp:10054:12"/> Whereby it ſhoulde folowe, that when Ihon dyd baptyſe, and ſende or directe men vntoo Ieſus, that he dyd baptyſe &amp; directe or ſende them vntoo a bare man. Whych thinge how vngodly it is, who doth not ſee? Ihon Baptiſt dyd knowe Chriſte to be the ſonne of god, equall w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the father in all thynges, he knew alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpirite of god did inhabyte and dwell in hym, whych was geuen vnto hym af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter no meaſure,<note place="margin">Ihon .i. Chapter.</note> but of whoſe fulneſſe all men did receyue. Ihon .i. Chapter. For this cauſe he attributeth ſo muche vntoo Chriſt, that he did ſend all men vnto him and prepared the people for hym. Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore he dydde baptyſe theym in the name of Ieſus, becauſe that he knewe hym too be one god with the father and the holy ghoſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe be thy rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons, &amp; not the word of god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>I wyl proue the theſe thinges by the worde of god. When Ihon did baptiſe Chriſte in Iordan, the heauens did open, &amp; he did ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of god deſcending and comming doun vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. And behold a voice from heauen, ſaying: Thys is my welbeloued ſon, In who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am pleaſed. Who wil ſay now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ihon knew not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt.
<pb facs="tcp:10054:13"/> Ihon .iij.<note place="margin">Ihon .iii. Chapter.</note> Chap. He dothe celebrate and ſet furth with manye goodly praiſes, the maieſtie of Chriſte, emong al other thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, ſpeakyng after this maner: He who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god hath ſent, ſpeaketh the word of god. For god doth not geue hym the ſpiryte after a meaſure. The father loueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon and hath giuen al thynges into his hand Theſe thinges doo teſtifye and wytneſſe that Ihon dyd knowe ryght well the mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtery of the trinitie and vnytye in Chriſte</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>I graunt that he did know as thou ſaieſt, yet it foloweth not therby that Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did baptyſe in the name of the father, the ſonne, and the holy goſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>It foloweth plainely. For I do aſke the whether he that baptizeth in Chriſt, doth baptyſe in man, or in god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
               <p>In god truely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe I aſke whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt touching his own godheade be ſeperated from the father &amp; the holye ghoſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
               <p>No, for there is but one god onely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>Now make thine ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gument after this maner: Chriſte Ieſus touching his diuine nature, is not dyuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt. And he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> baptizeth in Ieſus, baptizeth not in his humain nature, but in his diuine and
<pb facs="tcp:10054:13"/> godly nature. Ergo, he that baptizeth in Ieſus, baptizeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holye goſt. Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as it is proued before) did bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe in Ieſus Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, in hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhould come after him: Ergo, Ihon dyd baptiſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt, for theſe ſentences are of lyke ſyngnificacion and importaunce: he did baptiſe in god, he did baptiſe in Ieſus Chriſt, he dyd baptiſe in the name of the father, the ſonne and the holy goſt. For, there is one god onely vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to whom we are brought, and grafted by baptiſme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMO,</speaker>
               <p>I neuer vnderſtode this thyng afore, for I thought that Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had onely begon with hys baptiſm, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the baptiſme of Chriſte had the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at length begonne, when he dyd ſende his apoſtles in the laſt chapter of Mark, and of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew. Whiche thyng if it were true, the baptiſme of Ihon, and the baptiſme of Chriſt coulde not be all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>Of thys dyd come and ſpringe the errour of of the Anabaptiſtes. Becauſe that they thinke, that baptiſm was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ordeyned &amp; inſtituted after that Chriſte did ryſe from death. And I do merueyle, that they did falle in too thys errour, ſithens that with playne teſtymonyes of the ſcryptures it
<pb facs="tcp:10054:14"/> is ſet forth and expreſſed, that Chriſt had by his apoſtles, baptized before his death and afore that they had receiued the holy ghoſtes Ihon .iii.<note place="margin">Ihon .iii. and .iiii. Chapter.</note> and .iiii. Chapter. After thys Ieſus dyd come and his diſcyples, into the lande of Iuery, and there he did abyde with them, and did baptiſe. Ihon alſo dyd baptyſe before Chriſt, wherfore he was called baptyſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, baptyſme hath hys beginnynge and inſtitutyon of man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
               <p>Truly Ihon was a man, whych thing no man can denye, yet notwythſtanding, his doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne and baptyſme, were not of man, but of God.<note place="margin">Math. xxi. Chapter.</note> Mathewe one and twenty Chapter. But it is called the baptyſme of Ihon, and of the apoſtles, not becauſe it is theyrs, but becauſe it is mynyſtred by theym. I wyll ſpeake more playne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.<note place="margin">Math. xi. Chapter. how thys ſayinge. The lawe and the prophetes were tyll Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cam.</note> Chriſt. Mathewe .xi. Chapter, ſaythe that the law and the prophetes were tyll Ihon came, whereby Chriſte doth ſhew that the thynge that the Prophetes dyd afore prophecye, to be or too come, was more fullye ſet furthe and declared by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachyng of Ihon. For the thynges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> afore by the prophetes were prophecied to come, vnder darke fygures of wordes
<pb facs="tcp:10054:14"/> the ſelfe ſame thinges are ſette furthe by Ihon, as fulfylled and preſente,<note place="margin">Ihon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynneth wyth hys baptſme, the goſpell and newe teſtament.</note> and are in a maner ſhewed with the fygure. The lawe had a miſticall lambe: Ihon dydde ſhewe the true lambe wyth hys fynger. Ihon therfore doth begyn firſt the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and the newe Teſtamente, and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that the Meſſias is come. It was neceſſarye then, that he ſhould aboliſſhe the olde ſygnes, and chaunge them into other, that ſhould be without bloud, wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy of the new teſtamente.<note place="margin">Circumcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on is chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged intoo baptiſme.</note> For circumci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion was chaunged into baptyſme. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore Ihon beginneth baptiſme firſt, as a ſigne or ſeale of the people of God. But let vs heare his owne wytneſſes and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonyes of that thynge.<note place="margin">Math. iii. Chapter.</note> Mat. iii chap When he did ſe manye of the Pharyſes and Saduces, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming too his baptyſme (that they alſo might receiue baptiſm of him) he ſaid vnto them: Bryng ye furth frutes, worthy of repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wordes Ihon doth plainlye declare, wherfore, &amp; for what purpoſe &amp; vſe, he did miniſter baptiſm, although he ſhuld ſaie, It ſhal not be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to haue your body waſſhed in the water, but rather this, ye muſt haue a reſpect vnto, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye be new me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10054:15"/> that ye be ſory and repente of your myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes that are paſſed, and take heede of them, that are to come. There is no cauſe why ye ſhuld boſte your ſelues to be the children of Abraham, onleſſe ye do folow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth of Abraham. What did Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? he dyd beleue in god, hee was obediente vnto the worde of god, hee dyd approue hym ſelfe, or ſhewed hym ſelfe faythfull in all thinges vnto the ſame god. For I ſay vnto you, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god is able, to rayſe vnto Abraham, Chyldren of theſe ſtoones (that is to ſaye of the gentils) Now alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> axe is laid to the roote of the tree,<note place="margin">What is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bowes</note> wher wyth the vnprofytable braunches that bring forth no fruyte, are cutte of. That is to ſaye, the bowghes, that dyd growe of the naturall olyue tree, I meane thee vnfaythefull Chyldren, beynge cutte of and caſt awaye from the Teſtamente of god, ſhal be deſtroyed and burnt. Vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande therfore my wordes a ryght. Pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare your heartes agaynſt the comming of the Meſſias, the newe king, I do bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe you wyth water, and in a maner ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate you, or giue you the firſt inſtruction in the religyon of Chriſt, to the intente y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye be ſuch, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil repente &amp; receiue Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:10054:15"/> When he is receiued, he ſhal baptiſe you with the holye ghoſte, that is to ſaye,<note place="margin">Too bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> holi ghoſt</note> he ſhal ſeale and make you perfect, with his holy ſpirite, he ſhall pardon and forgeue you your ſynnes, he ſhall alſo endue you wyth fyer, that is to ſaye, wyth feruente charytye. Study wyth all diligence to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue hym worthely. &amp;c. By theſe teſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monies we do conclude and gather, that Ihon dydde baptyſe fyrſte, and that he dyd alſo baptiſe in Chriſte. The apoſtles after that they had receyued Chriſt, dyd vſe none other baptyſme, but the ſame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had learned of Ihon. Yea, Chriſte hym ſelfe was alſoo baptyzed in the bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſme of Ihon.<note place="margin">The bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of Ihon, is the true baptiſme, els Chriſt, was not well bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</note> Yf Ihons baptyſme is not trewe, it foloweth that Chryſte was not truely baptyzed, and that he oughte too be baptyzed agayne. Who is ſoo madde too ſay ſo? Ergo, the baptyſme of Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is the true baptiſme, whych Chryſt dyd confyrme and ſanctyfye in him ſelfe</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>I doo agre vntoo all theſe thynges: but what doo they make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte rebaptyzatyon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA</speaker>
               <p>Thys trewlye, that the men of Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, whome mentyon is made of, Actes. the nynetene Chapter. Were not bapty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zed
<pb facs="tcp:10054:16"/> again, ſyth that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of Chriſt and the baptiſme of Ihon be all one. Yf they were not baptyzed agayne, the ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baptiſtes haue no example at all, of theyr rebaptyzation. Whereby it foloweth, that theyr rebaptyzatyon is not of God For they deuyde that one onelye bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſme. Paule ſayth. One god, one fayth one baptyſme, whyche is in the churche of god, wythout the whych, there is noo baptyſme. Syth then that the anabapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes do forſake the church,<note place="margin">The ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes haue no baptiſme.</note> yea, do deuide the churche, and are felowes of heryty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, they haue noo baptyſme. For they are not in the churche of Chriſte. Ergo. theyr rebaptyzatyon is repugnaunte vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>too GOD, and is nothynge elles, but a newe ſecte, agaynſte the vnytye of the churche.<note place="margin">Obiection both foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhye and chyldyſhe.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
               <p>But thou doeſt diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble this, that they do abhorre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of the buſſhop of Rome, none otherwiſe then in tymes paſſed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy fathers dyd abhorre the baptyſme of heretykes, or minyſtred by heritykes. For they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had bene baptyzed by herytykes and ſcyſma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tikes, were baptyzed agayne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>Who dydde euer baptyſe men wyth the baptyſme of the Buſſhoppe of Roome?
<pb facs="tcp:10054:16"/> Dyd the buſſhop of Roome begyn bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>No, Ihon did begyn baptiſme, but the buſſhops of Rome did adde manye thinges of theyr owne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
               <p>The thynges that were added by the buſſhop of Roome, as ſalte Oyle, coniurynges, &amp;c. are they bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, or parte of baptyſme?<note place="margin">Thoughe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of Roome haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded many thyngs to baptiſme, yet it ought not to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Byſhope of Rome.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON</speaker>
               <p>Neyther of them, for then, neither Chriſt nor Ihon, had baptyzed truely, whyche dyd not adde thoſe thinges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA</speaker>
               <p>If theſe new added thinges are not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſme, nor yet parte thereof, whye do ye call it then the baptyſme of the buſſhop of Roome? Or was euer anye man that dyd baptyſe in the name of Clemente, Bonyface, Leo, or Gregorye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMO</speaker>
               <p>No manne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
               <p>In what then were ye baptyzed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>In the name of the father, of the ſonne, and of the holye ghoſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
               <p>Ergo, ye were not baptyzed in the baptyſme of the Buſſhop of Roome, but in the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſme of GOD. And they that baptiſe you nowe, in what, or wyth what wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des doo they baptyſe you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SYMON.</speaker>
               <p>With water, and in the name of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of the ſonne, and of the holye ghoſt</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:10054:17"/>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>Were ye baptized in the ſame and with the ſame worde in your youth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>Yes truely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>What neadeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys laſte baptiſme? doeſt thou not ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye are ſtarke madde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>When we were children we knew nothyng of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. We vow now vnto god purenes, &amp; a lyfe without ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>Could ye not do this without baptiſm? Yf ye could, ye neded no water, yf ye coulde not, the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water. Ergo, our ſaluatyon is alligated and bounde to the elementtes, agaynſte the nature of faythe and of the ſcriptures. What anſwere canſte thou make here.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>It is better, that we thus conſecrate our ſelues vnto god.<note place="margin">Anabaptiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes are like vnto mon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO</speaker>
               <p>As monkes did heare before tymes bynd themſelues vnto god with there vowes. Here poyſon is hydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye do chalenge nad attribute vnto your ſelues pureneſſe of lyfe, ye do deteſt &amp; abhorre other as vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clean, &amp; as the catharians in times paſſed ye do gather and aſſemble vnto your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues a peculiar churche, markyng and ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng your ſelues as though ye were the pureſt of all men.<note place="margin">Rebapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation is a newe ſecte againſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnytye of the church</note> Wherfore I may well cal your rebaptizatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a newe ſecte againſt the vnitye of the churche, whiche thynge
<pb facs="tcp:10054:17"/> appeareth more and more by thy words Tell me, I praye the, if youre churche is without ſinnes, or is no more in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe where is then the loſt &amp; prodigall chylde the ſtraying ſhepe, the fyeld ſowen with cockle and darnel, the net that draweth all kindes of fiſſhes, the ſupper or banket where all they that are bidden, doo ſitte alſo they that haue not the bridegromes liuerie. Yf ye be pure &amp; wholl, then haue ye no nede of Chriſt, the phiſition of the ſoules. O moſte bolde and ſhameles hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrytes, O diſguyſed and maſked hery tykes, who hath bidden you, to make dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiſion afore tyme? Or if ye be ſo holye &amp; pure, when wyll ye of charitye, beare w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, our heauy burthens, wherewyth we are ouercharged and burdoned, that ye maye fulfyll the lawe of Chriſte? When wyll ye haue compaſſyon of our infyrmi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties? When wyll ye that are ſtrong, take vs that are weake, vntoo you? Whye do ye cut of and contempne the ſicke and weak members? What are ye but ſciſma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tykes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt not yet told why the aunciente fathers dyd baptyſe them agayne, that had bene baptized by heritykes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
               <p>They were not
<pb facs="tcp:10054:18"/> baptized againe,<note place="margin">It is no baptiſme onleſſe it be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, the ſonne, and of the holy ghoſte.</note> but they were baptized as they that had not bene baptized. For herytykes dyd denie the trinitie, the god head of Chriſte, and the holy ghoſt. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, they were not of the churche: Ergo, they had no baptiſme, nor did bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Ieſus, whom they dyd denye. Moreouer, the cuſtome of rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizyng, or baptyzing agayn, was not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vſed in the church. For they that had bene baptyzed in the name of the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, of the ſonne, and of the holy ghoſt, were not baptyzed agayne, but were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued by the impoſition of handes, and alſo were admoniſſhed to perſiſte and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in the ſinceritie of fayth. This there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore helpeth you nothynge, but rather doth make againſt you. Emong the true chriſtians, ye haue no exaumple at all of your rebaptization, but emong theſe aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyent heritikes, that haue bene alreadye condempned of the churche. For ye doo renew the hereſyes of Aupentius.<note place="margin">The Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes do renew olde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyes.</note> Noua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus &amp; Pelagius.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>What maner of men were they.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>In the yere of our lorde .CC.lv. there roſe in Roome, a ceraine man, called Nauatus, a verye ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogante, proude, obſtinate and bold man
<pb facs="tcp:10054:18"/> He did teache,<note place="margin">Nonatus errour.</note> that a man after baptiſme was pure and cleane, which pureneſſe yf he had ones loſt through ſinne, he coulde neuer be forgyuen. And if anye man for feare and dreade, or neceſſitie of deathe, had denied Chriſte, that he ought not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more to be receyued intoo the church (thoughe he lamented neuer ſo ſore for hys fall) but that he oughte to be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, and as a dampned creature, too be ſhunned of all men. Thys thynge dydde cauſe a counſayle of graue and holy men to be gathered at Roome,<note place="margin">A counſall agaynſt Nouatus.</note> whiche by the ſcriptures, beynge truelye vnderſtanded did condempne this opinion, as vngodly and herytycall. Yet in the meane ſeaſon, Nouatus dothe not leaue of, nor yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant his vngodly opinion: but rather did aſſemble and gather a peculyar churche, condempning the churches, where ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and repentaunt perſonnes were, he dydde call hys churche pure. Therefore were the Nouatyans,<note place="margin">Why the Nouatia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wer called Cathari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> called Cathary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Whome he dydde receyue into his church, them did he bind vnto his errour &amp; conſecrate vnto his vnpure clenlynes, by reqaptizatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or baptizing again. I do not bring theſe thinges out of mine own head,
<pb facs="tcp:10054:19"/> but out of thoſe auncyent doctours, Cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nelius, Ciprianus, Dioneſius, Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus, and Euſebius. Of whome ſome did lyue in Nouatus time.<note place="margin">The No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatians &amp; Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes are lyke in all thynges.</note> Now if thou doſt diligently loke vpon theſe auncyent No<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uatians, &amp; the anabaptyſtes of our tyme y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt find very litle difference betwene them, for as Nouatus beinge openly con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinced in that moſt famous counſayle of learned Biſhops, doth not forſake hys errour, but obſtinately dothe defende it. ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Anabaptiſtes do at this preſent. For howe often haue they bene ouerthrowen in the open diſputations, that haue bene kepte wyth them in Tigure, Sanctogal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, Berne, Baſile, Conſtance, Argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne, and Auguſte? And yet for all that, they wyl rather looſe theyr lyfe, then for ſake theyr errour: yea, they do gather &amp; aſſemble peculier churches, they baptiſe agayne, they condempne oure churches as vncleane, they doo atribute vnto them ſelues, pureneſſe of lyfe, to be ſhorte, they doo all thynges that Nouatus dydde. In the meane ſeaſon, they are ambitious, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogante, proude, pufte vp, and verye hipo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crytes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>I vnderſtande that the Anabaptyſtes are Nouatyans.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10054:19"/>
               <p>What ſayeſt thou of the other two?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>IA.</speaker>
               <p>Aupentius was buſſhop of Milan,<note place="margin">Aupenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us condem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth the baptiſme of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> afore Ambroſius, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſect of Arrius. He did condempne the baptiſme of children His errour was condempned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle of Miluent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>But it fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loweth not thereby, that infantes muſte be baptyzed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
               <p>Verelye it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, whych thyng we wyll proue by and by.</p>
            </sp>
            <div n="2" type="dialogue">
               <head>¶ The ſecond Dialogue. That the baptyſme of children, is of God.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>Whatſoeuer thou ſayeſt, I wyll proue by moſt ſtronge argumentes, that the baptiſme of children is not of god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IADA.</speaker>
                  <p>And I wyll gladly heare howe thou canſt do it.<note place="margin">The chyef Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of infantes.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>In the laſt of Marke, Chriſte ſayth to hys apoſtles go throughout all the wholl worlde, and preach the goſpell to euery creature. He that beleueth and is baptyzed, ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued: He that beleueth not, ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempned. Alſo in the laſte of Mathewe it is wrytten after this maner: Al power is giuen vnto me in heauen, and in earth goyng therfore teache ye al nations, bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tizing
<pb facs="tcp:10054:20"/> in the name of the father, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon and of the holy ghoſt. By theſe it ſemeth to folow, and that neceſſarely, that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme ought onely to be miniſtred vntoo them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can be taught and inſtructed. For he ſayth firſt, teache them, and then after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes: baptyſe them, whereby it folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth alſo, that baptiſme is a ſigne of the faith that wente before. For he ſaithe: he that beleueth and is baptyzed ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, Let vs nowe adde and ioyne vntoo theſe, and ponder dilygently both the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amples and factes of Ihon, and of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and that whych I ſay ſhalbe ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſte and playne. For Ihon dyd bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe them onelye, that dyd confeſſe theyr ſinnes.<note place="margin">Actes .ii. Chapter.</note> Actes .ii. Chap. Luke doth wryte after this maner: And they which recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued gladlye the worde, were baptyzed. Philip doth then at lengthe baptyſe the ſtewarde of Quene Candace, after that he had declared vnto him. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. liii. Chap. of Eſay, &amp; had queſtioned wyth him of his faith.<note place="margin">Actes. viii. Chapter.</note> Actes. viii. chapter. All the apoſtles after that they had preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and that the faith was receyued, did baptiſe the faithefull. It foloweth then, that baptyſme as a ſigne is due vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10054:20"/> that can both heare and receyue the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne. Infantes, becauſe that they want the vſe of reaſon, can neyther heare nor receyue the doctryn, &amp; therfore they haue no faythe. For Paule teacheth that faith commeth by hearynge, and hearyng by the word of god. Rom. x. Chap,<note place="margin">Roma .x.</note> Sith then that Children can neyther heare, nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande the worde of god, they can not beleue. Ergo baptiſme is not due vntoo them, which is a ſigne of the faythe that goeth before. Yf thou canſte,<note place="margin">A ſolution to the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baptiſtes.</note> anſwere me to theſe: I wil tell and ſet forth, myne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther argumentes hereafter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou haſt reherſed the chief and principal foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>datyons of the Anabaptyſtes, that haue anye ſhowe or appearaunce, but thys is noo newe thynge vnto vs, whych haue learned and red in hyſtories, that aboue three hundreth, xlviii. yeares agone that is to ſaye, in the yeare of Chriſte. M.C. lxxxii. there haue bene heretykes,<note place="margin">The ſum of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baptiſtes argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> that haue taught the ſame doctrine. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye do leane vpon a weake &amp; bric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kel foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, your fote ſhal eaſely be ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerted &amp; ouerthrowen, in al your doctrin ye do moſt vrgently beat this into mens hedes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme is a ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull
<pb facs="tcp:10054:21"/> or of them that haue faith alredy. Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes or yonge babes haue no fayth. Ergo baptiſme ought not to be miniſtred vnto infantes. In very dede (if the wordes be wel and truly expounded and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) we do gladly graunt this thinge vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you: That baptyſme is a ſygne of the faithfull people. But we do not deffyne, cyrcumſcribe,<note place="margin">This word fidelis, faithfull or fidel ought not to be limited as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts wil haue it</note> or limite the faythful, as ye do: for yf no man ſhoulde be baptiſed but they that beleue truly, and from a ſincere hearte, Iudas, Simon, of Samaria, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas. and other hipocrites, had neuer ben baptized. Let no man thus take my ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, although I would haue baptyſme to be miniſtred vnto theym, whome it is manyfeſte and playne to be infydels, but myne intente is to ſhewe, that by thys word, fidelis, faythfull, ſome what more is to be vnderſtanded, then the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes do expreſſe,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
                  <p>What canſt thou make of a faythfull but a faythfull? I can not vnderſtand how infantes and yong babes can be faithful, ſith that they do wante the vſe of reaſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>But in thys buſyneſſe, we do ſoo ſpeake of the faythfull that we do in noo wiſe exclude
<pb facs="tcp:10054:21"/> the children from the number of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſyth that the children and infantes are of god whome god doth alwaies admitte and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue into his churche emonge the fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>It behoueth the to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the ſame,<note place="margin">Who be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fideles &amp; faythfull. Gene. xvii Chapter. O comfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, both to vs and too oure children.</note> as I haue alredy proued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
                  <p>I wil proue it. Geneſis xvii. chapi. Where god doth make a coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunt with Abraham. the lorde doth pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culyarly comprehend the chyldren in the couenaunt, for he ſayth. <hi>I ſhall be thy god, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god of thy ſede after the.</hi> And afterwards he commaundeth the infantes to be cyrcum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed vpon the eyght daye, &amp; to receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of the Teſtament. Wherby it folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that god is not only the god of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be of age, and canne beleue in God, but alſo of the infante,<note place="margin">Children are fideles or faithful and be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſte.</note> which for lacke of age can not yet beleue, for they through grace and the promyſe, are receyued in to the couenaunt and number of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>I care not for the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente of the Iewes, theſe olde thynges are aboliſhed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>By Ieſu Chriſt the ceremonies are aboliſhed and
<pb facs="tcp:10054:22"/> the figures fulfylled,<note place="margin">What parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolyſhed by Chriſt.</note> but the couenaunte made with Abraham, ſtandeth ſtyll. El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les god were not our god, and the God of our ſede, and ſhuld be made by Chriſt more vnmerciful and more ſtraunge, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was to the aunciaunte fathers before Chriſt. Which to thynke, were a foolyſh thyng, that I ſhould not ſay an vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſpecially ſyth that in the newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente,<note place="margin">The fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full are the chyldren of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Roma. iiii. Gala. iiii. Mat. viii. Luke .xiii. and .xix. Chapter. Ihon .i. Chapter.</note> alſoo the faythfull are called the chyldren of Abraham. Rom. iiii. Gal. iiii Mat. viii. Luk. xiii. &amp; .xix. Chap. Beſides theſe, Chriſt w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> expreſſe words, doth ſay: Suffer yonge children to come vnto me, for to ſuche doth belong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Paul ſpeaking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians, ſaithe: Youre chyldren are cleane: How ſhould that be, onleſſe it were tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row grace, mercy, &amp; the promiſe of god? It foloweth then, that the children of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtians, are of god, &amp; ought to be num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bred emong the children of god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe thinges do altogether repugne vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the ſcriptures and goſpell, as thoughe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> carnall birth ſhould auaile ſome thyng before god, wheras Ihon ſaith: Whych were not borne of bloud, nor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> will of the fleſh, or of man, but were born of god
<pb facs="tcp:10054:22"/> Ye ſay that the chyld doth belong to the church, becauſe that his parentes are of the churche.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>We doo ſaye thys through the grace &amp; mercy of god, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of is the promiſe: The children are of the churche, not for theyr carnall generation &amp; birth, but for the promiſe of god, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he hath promyſed, that he wil be the god of the children.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>What if the parentes of the childe,<note place="margin">Whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of them, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feygne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to beleue ought to be bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tized Act. viii. Chapter</note> ſhuld feigne their fayth, and not beleue truely: ſhould not theſe children be borne of vnchriſtian pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rentes, and therfore ought not to be bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyzed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>I aſke the, Symon, dyd Symon Magus of Samaria, beleue or not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>He dyd not beleue, but he did feygne hym ſelfe to beleue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOI</speaker>
                  <p>What yf thy ſayinges be repugnaunte vnto the ſcriptures?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not thinke it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>I will ſhewe the ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Act. viii. chap. it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after this maner: When they of Samaria had gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen credyte vnto Philippe, which prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto them of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of god, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Ieſu Chriſt, they were bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tized both men &amp; women. Then dyd Si<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon Magus beleue alſo and being bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tized dyd ioyne hymſelfe, too Philippe</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10054:23"/>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>He did beleue, that is to ſay he did confeſſe the faith with his mouth and ſayd that he did beleue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIADA</speaker>
                  <p>This y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſay, this word fidele, or faithful is of a larger ſygnificatyon, and can not be ſo narowly taken, which thinge thou thy ſelfe doſt graunte with me, being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrayned therto, by the aucthoritie of the ſcriptures. But I aſke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, why did Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyp baptiſe hym, ſith that he dyd not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue truely? Diddeſt thou not ſay before that baptyſme oughte too be myniſtred vnto no man, except he doth beleue true<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly? and that baptiſm is a ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith that goeth afore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſaide wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, that he did beleue in Chriſte, Philyp dothe not ſe the hearte, but being contente wyth the confeſſyon of the mouth, doth pronounce and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe.<note place="margin">God only ſeeth the hearte.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>So thou ſhuldeſt haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken and confeſſed, that god onelye ſeeth the heart, and that we oughte to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the outward confeſſyon, &amp; vpon this confeſſion to baptiſe. Sith then that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infant, doth confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his mouthe, and ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he beleueth in Chriſt Ieſus, moreouer doth beleue and confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god is his god, &amp; the god of his
<pb facs="tcp:10054:23"/> ſede, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth therefore brynge hys chylde vnto baptiſme, it is conuenient &amp; mete, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we beleue his wordes: &amp; thoughe ſome time we doubt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, yet know we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the chylde ſhall not beare the iniquitye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the carnall generation doth make nothynge to this, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are, and ſhal be called the children of god, which partayne too the free election and gratuite promyſe of god. Do not all men knowe,<note place="margin">Ezechias.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ezechias being a faithful king, was borne of a wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked parent? But yet this thing did harm or hinder him nothing at all:<note place="margin">Eſau.</note> euen as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau got no profit therby, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was borne of a godly parent: ergo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> election of god doth remain fre.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>What if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> child y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is brought to baptiſm, were not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect? were it not better y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ſhuld the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at length be baptized, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhuld ſe &amp; perceiue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elect? For they whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are not elected, are not of god, &amp; they that are not of god, ought not to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyzed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>When ſhuldeſt thou the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baptyſe him that came at the euening in too the vineyarde? when ſhouldeſt thou baptiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thief on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe? By this mean no man ſhould be baptized, and baptiſm
<pb facs="tcp:10054:24"/> ſhoulde be abolyſhed, for the electyon of god, is not alwaies knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs: yea, we ſhulde by that meane, take that vpon vs which belongeth to god only:<note place="margin">God only knoweth who be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and who be not.</note> for god onely doth ſearche the heart &amp; knoweth only, which be elected, &amp; which be not. I do let paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we coulde not thus auoyd the hipocrites. For Simon Magus did feigne his faith wherby ye anabaptiſtes do iudge &amp; meaſure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> election, and yet he was not elected.<note place="margin">Iſmael and Eſau were not elected, &amp; they were cyrcum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed.</note> Other that are alredy of age may do the ſame. But tell me, were Iſmael, and Eſau elected or not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM</speaker>
                  <p>They were not elected.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>When they were yet babes and infantes, were they numbred emong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god, or not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>I can not tell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>But it behoued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to know it, ſyth that thou takeſſe ſuche matters in hand. That they wer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of god, I proue it by the circumciſion They were circumciſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of god: circumciſion was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of the people of god, ergo, in their infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie they were the children of god, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they weare of the people of god, yea, though they were not elected. It is plain and manifeſte by the lyfe that folowed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they were not elected and choſen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10054:24"/>
                  <p>I could wel graunt, that they were of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god, but I can not recken them emonge the faythefull.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>Are not they, that be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god, faithful?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>They that be of age are faithfull infantes and yonge babes, can not be ſo for they can not profeſſe theyr faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO</speaker>
                  <p>Ye ſynge alwayes one ſonge, haſte thou not heard a great while agone, that chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, though they can not confeſſe theyr fayth, are rekened emonge the faythfull Or is god onely the god of them that are of age, and not alſo of the chyldren? Or dyd Chriſt ſuffer onely for them that are of age, and not alſo for the Chyldren?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>He dyd ſuffer for the ſatyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factyon of all the ſynnes of the whole world.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
                  <p>Haue the Chyldren anye ſynne?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>They haue the origynall ſynne.<note place="margin">Chyldren are reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Chryſte, and not only they that be of age.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
                  <p>Syth then that Paule ſayeth, that whatſoeuer was fallen by Adam, the ſame was reſtored by Chriſte, and not onely they, that be of age, but alſo Chyldren, be loſte in A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dam, It foloweth that children are reſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red agayne by Chriſt, Yf they be reſtored by Chryſt, they are of God, &amp; ought to be
<pb facs="tcp:10054:25"/> ſealed, with the ſeale of the people of god Baptiſme is the ſeale of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god Ergo, chyldren ought too be baptyzed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>Proue that baptiſme is the ſigne or ſeale of the people of god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOI</speaker>
                  <p>I proue that by your owne confeſſyon. For ye ſay that baptiſme is the ſygne of the faythfull.<note place="margin">Actes. x. Chapter. What is to receue the holy ghoſte.</note> I proue beſydes, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of Peter, whyche Actes. x. Chapter ſpeaketh after thys maner. Whoo can forbyd them to be baptyzed, that haue re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued the holy goſt as well as we?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>MON.</speaker>
                  <p>But children haue not receiued the holye ghoſte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>In this place to receyue the holy goſt, is too receyue a wytnes that we are of god, whych recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth vs, and that we are clenſed and pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged by god.<note place="margin">Act. x. xi. xv. Chap.</note> This may be proued by the x. xi. and .xv. Chapter of Actes. Chyldren are clenſed &amp; purged by God: ergo, they haue the ſpiryte of god. If they haue the ſpiryt of god, they are of God, and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is due vntoo them: as it is ſuffycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proued by the olde and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SYMON.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf Chriſt ſhould ſay The kyngdome of heauen belongeth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to them, I would eaſely agre to the, but he ſayth not vnto them, but vnto ſuche.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10054:25"/>
                  <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
                  <p>But thou moſt thynke and conſyder, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there muſt be ſome lykeneſſe and affinitye betwen the thinges that are compared together. I can not ſaye, If thou wylt be ſaued, do as Iudas dyd, for Iudas is not ſaued: but damned. If the chyldren wer not of god, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of heauen theirs: the Lorde had not ſaide. Yf ye wyll enter into the kyngdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: be ye made as theſe chyldren are. Therfore when he ſayeth: vnto ſuche, he ſheweth that chyldren are ſuch, as he wil haue them to be, that are of god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>It were better, to proue with expreſſe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonyes of the ſcripture, that children haue the ſpiryte of god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
                  <p>By what argumentes, wylte thou haue thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges that are playne and manyfeſt, to be proued vnto the? But heare thou, a more playne teſtimonye. Paule. Romaine. viii. faythe: that he that hath not the ſpirite of god, is not his. Wherby it foloweth that he, which is of god, hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of god, the chyldren are of god: Ergo, they haue the ſpirit of god.<note place="margin">Children haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of god</note> Yf thei haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of god, then ought thei by good ryght to be baptized. For Peter ſayeth: who can for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byd them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue receuid the holy ghoſt,
<pb facs="tcp:10054:26"/> to be baptyzed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>I wyll not contende. Howe beit I merueyl, that it is ſo expreſſely ſaid. Teche ye, baptizyng. Agayn, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter baptized the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued gladly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde: ſo lykewiſe Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip did baptiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſteward of Quene Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dace.<note place="margin">Howe the places ale<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged by the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtes ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>Both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places and examples, which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt brought &amp; aleged, ought to be vnderſtanded of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are of age, and not of chyldren. Chriſt did not ſende hys diſciples to preche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel vnto chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were of age &amp; had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of reaſon. Nor we do not teache, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> children ought to be baptiſed in thoſe places, wher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel was neuer preched. But wher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god &amp; the holy goſpel, hath ben both preched &amp; alſo receiued by faith, it is no dout, but there it is both taught &amp; bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are of god, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil of god, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which be of god ſhould be ſealed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> baptiſm, &amp; in a maner brought vnto god.<note place="margin">The doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is greter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> baptiſm</note> Therfore they are not excluded from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god, but are re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued and rekened emonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god. Or elles tell me Symon, whether of the twoo is greater, baptiſme or the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>The doctryne is grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter than Baptyſme.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
                  <p>What
<pb facs="tcp:10054:26"/> is the doctrine?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
                  <p>The holy goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel: For Marke ſaith: Go thoroughout all the wholle worlde, and preche the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell vnto euery creature: Mathewe lyke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe: Teache them to kepe what ſoeuer I haue commaunded you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
                  <p>Dothe then thys goſpell teache that the chyldren are not of God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>No, elles it ſhould be harder &amp; more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull then the lawe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIO.</speaker>
                  <p>Doth Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande his diſcyples to preache that chyldren oughte too be reiected and caſte awaye?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON?</speaker>
                  <p>Noo, But rather he dothe chyde hys dyſcyples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that they rebuked theym, that broughte children vnto hym.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIAD</speaker>
                  <p>Thus I doo conclude then, ſyth that in theſe wordes of Chryſte. (Teache Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe) the doctryne is more excellente and greater, and yet chyldren are not forbyd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den it, but rather broughte vnto it: It fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loweth that they are not forbydden bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſme, which is leſſe,<note place="margin">Infantes that dye without baptiſme are notte dampned</note> but rather ought to be brought vnto it. Thus it is manyfeſt and playne, that thys commaundement of Chriſt ſtandeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, and not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſhuld folow y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the infants which die w<hi rend="sup">o</hi>ut baptiſm, are not dampned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10054:27"/>
                  <p>That foloweth plainly, &amp; alſo this dothe folowe, that thou being ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men with the truth, doſt ſeke how to bring me into an other purpoſe, leaſt I ſhould bind the more ſtraightly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſſe that I can ſay nothinge againſte ſo manyfeſt truthe. But I haue broughte this of the children, to the intent that thou ſhuldeſt teache and inſtructe me in thys poynte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>Iuſtifying &amp; ſaluatyon is much leſſe bound to the outward elements the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in tymes paſſed in the law.<note place="margin">Why the infante is baptiſed.</note> Heb. ix. chap The infante therfore is not baptized for this intent, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by baptiſm, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaie: by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward waſſhyng of water, he ſhuld be made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> child of god, but he is therfor bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tized becauſe he was afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> child of god throughe grace &amp; promiſe. Wherefore if they die afore that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water of baptiſm be poured vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they are neuertheles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of god, &amp; are ſaued through the grace and promyſſe of god, by the force &amp; ſtrength of the couenaunt, by the ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he made on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, for all mankynde. In the generalitye of mankynd, not only they, that are of age, but alſo children are included.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
                  <p>By thys meane, we ſhuld nede no bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. For if the chylde is alredye before
<pb facs="tcp:10054:27"/> the chyld of god, what good doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? wherby this alſo ſhould folow, that baptiſme is bare water.<note place="margin">
                        <p>We ought to ſpeake reuerently of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes The oute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes &amp; ſignes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; lefte in neceſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie can not dampne one.</p>
                        <p>The bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of bloude.</p>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIAD.</speaker>
                  <p>We muſt ſpeake more reuerently of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes. None of the faithfull is ſo alliga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and bound to the elementes, and out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward thinges, that they may condemne him if they be omitted and left in neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie: for the bloude of Ieſus Chriſt, hath clenſed him. I do call neceſſitie, as when a chyld departeth before baptiſm, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man, beyng conuerted to the faith, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can be baptyzed, taken to martyr do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, which thing was often times done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primitiue churche, for vnto hym the croſſe was in ſteade of baptiſme, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the auncient fathers did call it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of bloud. Howbeit no man ought to neglecte or contempne the order that Chriſt hath inſtituted, nor to deſpyſe bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme, if he may haue it. If he contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth or doth neglect to receiue baptiſme when he may haue it, he is noo chriſtian, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſciple of Iulianus &amp; Porphirius For if baptiſm were vnprofitable, Chriſt would not haue inſtituted it. All thinges that Chriſte hath gyuen and lefte vntoo vs, are excellente, holye, and profytable.
<pb facs="tcp:10054:28"/> Ergo, baptiſm is not onely profitable vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs, but alſo moſte neceſſarye: Farther more, we do adde thys alſo, that baptiſm touchyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mattyer, is water, and yet it ought not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned and caſt awai, or eſtemed as the comon water of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> well. For the water is onely parte of it, and a certayne ſigne.<note place="margin">The whol action of baptiſme contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth great myſteryes</note> But the wholle action co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyneth a greate myſterye, and an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſacrament. Wherfore it was called by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy fathers, a purging, &amp; remiſſion of ſynnes, alſo, regeneracion or renuyng, and other lyke names. Not that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength to purge or renewe. For then Symon of Samaria, Iudas, Hime<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neus, Phyletus, and other falſe brethern and hipocrites had bene clenſed and renu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, for then were waſſhed with the water of Baptiſm. But it is playne and many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were not purged inwardely, but defiled with all iniquitye and wycked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, that they were not the chyldren of god, but the chyldren of the diuell. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore theſe godly &amp; ſpiritual things are attributed vnto baptiſme, they be not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward waſſhing, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl action, which conteyneth the faith of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſter, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church &amp; of him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is baptized, alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace, election &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb facs="tcp:10054:28"/> of god. It is then chiefly attributed vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, which is ſignifyed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pouryng on of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>what is ſignified the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?<note place="margin">What is ſignifyed by the pou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng on of the water.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>That he whych is baptized, is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god, &amp; that he is clenſed inward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of the holy ghoſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome water, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is waſſhed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of Chriſt. &amp; initiated vnto a new lyf, euen as water doth waſſhe and clenſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward filtheneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>verie well, Syth, then that the myſteries of batiſme are ſo hygh excellente, &amp; holy, why,<note place="margin">Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was in tymes paſſed, a great ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment.</note> I pray y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are they geuen &amp; miniſtred to infantes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are not able to receyue ſo excellent thinges?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO</speaker>
                  <p>Was not circumciſion in tymes paſſed, a great ſacrament, a ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god, &amp; an initiation or entraunce into the true fayth and innocency of lyfe. Deu. x. Hier. iiii. Roma ii &amp; iiii Cha. And yet it was geuen &amp; miniſtred to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che long after wer inſtructed in the lawe. Deu. vi. Whie ſhuld we not do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame? Why ſhuld we not ſeale our children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng newly born w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeale of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god? &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei be of age, bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into knowlege of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel? Of this,<note place="margin">Confirma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.</note> did ſpri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g among au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctant fathers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoping, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, an eſtablyſhyng of thoſe thinges, that were begonne in bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme.
<pb facs="tcp:10054:29"/> The chyldren were brought forthe, they were aſked of their faythe, of the Lordes prayer &amp; other neceſſary articles, wherin they were inſtructed &amp; confirmed. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they that dyd bryng the chyldren to baptiſm, are witneſſes that the child whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is brought, is borne of chryſtian pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, aſkyng both in theyr name, and in the parentes name, that the ſeale of the people of god may be geuen &amp; miniſtred vnto the childe. Wherfore they be called in oure vulgare tonge godfathers &amp; god motheres, becauſe that they brynge the chylde to god, and wytneſſe that he is of god, promyſing that they wyl bryng vp the chylde in the true fayth, if nede ſhuld require. Yf ye aſke, by what ſcripturs we do ſtrenghten theſe oure ſainges, we doo bryng vnto you the Analogye, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>encie of the ceremones of the olde lawe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, of circumciſion: For eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as in circumciſion the chyldren were brought vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, ſo we do read in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldren were brought vnto Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI</speaker>
                  <p>I do lette theſe thynges paſſe nowe, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne vnto the fyrſte. Thou dyddeſt ſay yf I remember well, that where Chriſt is not preached, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt be taught fyrſte
<pb facs="tcp:10054:29"/> and then at length baptized.<note place="margin">They ought not to goo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to baptiſe where the goſpell is not prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>So it is, nor it can be done none otherwyſe (as thou thy ſelf doeſt knowe) for yf any man ſhuld come in to Greekland where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Turke doth now raygn, &amp; there wold baptiſe, afore he had taught: ſhould not loſe his labour, for men beynge not yet taught what baptiſme is, or what it ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfieth, wold neyther the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues receyue baptiſme, nor ſuffer it to be miniſtred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their chyldren.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>Did not, I prai y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, the Iues knowe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god was their god &amp; the god of their chyldren?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>They kenw it ryght wel, &amp; therfore they circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>what nedeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ani preaching emong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knew god alredy before? Why did they not by &amp; by bryng &amp; intiate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children by baptiſme vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Chriſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>The Apoſtles did preache baptiſm againſt circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Iues w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> toth &amp; nail defended circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion. Therfore ther was nede of long preaching emong the Iues, that they myght vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme ſhuld be in ſted of circumciſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>The anabaptiſtes do ſay that ye teache theſe thynges without the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>Thei ſhuld eaſely vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſm is com in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtede of circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10054:30"/> if they woulde diligently looke vpon the vſe of them both. For in baptiſme, as in tymes paſſed in circumciſion, the name is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto chyldren. So it is wrytten. Luc ii chapter. But theſe thynges are of lytle weyght emong you. Therfore we do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre all our ſaynges to the Actes of the Apoſtles. x. xi. xv. and Colloſſe .ii. chapte. For there Paul doth comforte the fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full that were of the gentyles, &amp; byddeth them that they ſhuld not be ſory, becauſe they were not circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed: for why? Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme was the circumciſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythful.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>But there he doth playnely and with expreſſe wordes ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is done without handes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandyng therby a renewynge of the mynd &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>We ſpeak of none other. But in the meane ſeaſon Paule dothe meane that Iewyſſhe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcyſyon, that was done in the priuye membre wyth a flynte ſtone, and wyth handes. I ſaye that ye are cyrcumcyſed, O ye Colloſſenſes, and haue a cyrcumcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon, not that cyrcumcyſion that is done wyth handes, but in ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodelye &amp; outwarde circumciſion, ye haue Chriſtes circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, baptiſme. For as by circumci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb facs="tcp:10054:30"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuttyng away of affections was ſignified: ſo by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waſſhing, done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of baptiſm, the purging &amp; clenſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin, is fygurated &amp; betokened. That thys is the true meaning &amp; ſence of this place I wil proue by the very words of Paul In Chriſt (ſaith he) ye are complet, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of all rule &amp; power, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye are circumciſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the circumcyſion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is made wythout handes, when ye dyd put of the ſinfull body of the fleſh, by the circumciſion of Chriſt, being buried toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther with him, through baptiſme, in the which alſo ye be riſen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, by the faith wrought in you of god, which raiſed him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead. Bring hether to thys place y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> .vi. to the Rom. &amp; conferre them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſm is called the circumciſion of Chriſt, &amp; alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme hath bene placed in the ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> circumciſion. Vpon theſe things I do conclude after this maner: Yong childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were in times paſſed, circumciſed. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm occupieth the place &amp; roum of circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſion: ergo, our childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt be baptized</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>What, on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .viii. day?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>We are bound neither to time nor too place, but we are fre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thoſe thinges by Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:10054:31"/> Al thinges the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being conſidered,<note place="margin">We are free from al out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the lawe by Chriſt.</note> it is ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt and plaine, that the baptiſm of chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren is of god, againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which, ſith that the anabaptiſtes do repugne, it is wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt. that they do contrary the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell, the election of God, and the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting couenaunt. They are therfore ouer bold &amp; raſh, they are open violatours or breakers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couenaunt of god, vnfaith ful againſt god, ſith that they do exclude and debarre them from the couenaunt of God, whome gods grace dothe compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende in the couenaunte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet ye haue no expreſſe word of God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children ought to be baptized.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall not all that we haue hetherto aled<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged and brought, proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame? But go to, put the caſe that we haue no expreſſe word therof in the ſcriptures. Tell thou, where haue ye one expreſſe word y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ought not to be baptyzed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>Teache baptyzyng. Agayn: They came and confeſſed theyr ſinnes. Item: They that receiued the word gladly. were bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyzed.<note place="margin">Baptiſme is in the ſtead of cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumciſion.</note> And he that beleueth and is bapti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue anſwered alredy be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to all theſe: but ſo ye are wont to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate euery foote, your bald reaſons and
<pb facs="tcp:10054:31"/> argumentes.<note place="margin">The Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes are prompte &amp; quicke to ſpeake, but not redye to gyue place to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe.</note> For ye are very prompt &amp; quicke to ſpeake, but not ſo ready to giue place to the truth. I haue not yet hearde in all thine allegations, any ſuche ſaying or ſentence. Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought not to be bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tized.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>But that doth folow of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places afore alledged.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
                  <p>Thys is neither commaunded there, nor yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bydden. Beſydes that, your conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are falſe, and wythoute foundaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If ye be nothinge aſhamed of youre falſe conſequences, we wyll be nothinge aſhamed of our true. Therefore when ye crye out ſaying. Where doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture teach that children ought to be baptiſed? we crye agayne: Where doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture forbid to baptyſe them? Ye do anſweare in the laſt of Marke. We bring agaynſt you. Gene .xvii. Marke .x. i. Corinth. vii. Acte. x. Colloſſ. ii Chap. Moreouer, we do ſubmit theſe our ſayinges and writin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, to the iudgement of all godlye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Whether that it be more like vnto the truth, that they do exclude &amp; debarre the children whom Chriſt hath waſſhed with his bloud, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couenaunt of god (for why do they denye vnto them, the ſigne of the couenaunte: and of the clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge?)
<pb facs="tcp:10054:32"/> or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we do teche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children to be of god, redemed by Chriſt Ieſus, whom he biddeth &amp; wylleth to be brought vnto him, &amp; alſo too be baptized? Iudge thou Symon, and tell me whether of theim is more like to be true.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>If the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be conſidered by it ſelfe, all contentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being laid aſide, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ye ſay is moſte true, and moſt weightie. But this I doo wonder and maruaile at, that thou doſte ſay, that the baptiſme of children hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinued in the church, euer ſince the tyme of the apoſtles, which apoſtles did neuer baptiſe chyldren. Here I doo moſte ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire the to bringe furthe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer thou haſt yet in ſtore, I wyll gladly receyue all truthe: for manye of vs haue thought hetherto, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſm of children was brought in by the buſſhop of Rome</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="dialogue">
               <head>¶ The third Dialogue. That the baptyſme of chyldren hath contynued in the church of Chriſt, euer ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this time.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
                  <p>No man can denye, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the buſſhop of Rome &amp; the fathers haue added certaine things to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſm of Chriſt, but no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10054:32"/> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is wiſe, will ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it had his beginnyng of them, that is to ſay, that did begin the baptiſme of children. Thoſe things then that were added, and were repugnaunte vnto the word of god, were taken away againe, leſt any man ſhould make any bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſines for it. As for that, that ye bringe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, that the apoſtles did neuer bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſe children, no man lyuyng is able too proue it. For I wyll ſhew no ſmall argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, that the apoſtles did baptiſe chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, wherby y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt eaſely vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the baptiſme of children hath contynued in the church of Chriſt, euer ſince the apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles time, &amp; that it is no new inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the buſſhop of Rome.<note place="margin" type="runSum">i Certayne argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes againſt the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes.</note> Firſt, we do make our argument vpon the force &amp; ſtrength of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precept and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of chriſt &amp; of the doctrine, after this maner: Chriſt did ſend his diſciples to preche the goſpel &amp; to baptiſe: ergo, he did ſend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">The proue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quence, or argument</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>I denye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſequence</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>But I wil proue it after this maner It is ſo farre, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the goſpel ſhuld: reiecte &amp; caſt backe the chyldren, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it dothe rather bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto Chriſt. Now the doctrine is greater then baptiſme .i. Cor. i. cha. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, which is greater, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, the goſpel
<pb facs="tcp:10054:33"/> is the chyldrens, that then, which is laſſe that is to ſay, baptiſme ſhal be theirs, Er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>go, the apoſtles dyd baptiſe the chyldren</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">ij</note> The ſeconde argument may be made and gathered vpon the nature of him, to whome baptyſme is due, and whyche is able too receyue baptiſme. As manye as god doth recken emong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fideles or faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, they are fideles, or faithfull. For Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter dyd heare this ſayinge of the Lorde. That god hath purifyed or made cleane, call thou it not common or vncleane. Ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. x. chapter. He doth put the chyldren in the number of the faithfull: Ergo, the children are of the number of the fideles or faithfull, and oughte to be compted &amp; reputed of vs emong the fideles, or faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, onleſſe we will repugne againſt god and be ſtronger then he. Now it is moſt certayne, that the apoſtles did baptiſe all them that Chryſt commaunded them to baptyſe. Chriſte commaunded them too baptyſe the faythfull (as ye youre ſelues do graunt and confeſſe) Ergo, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did baptyſe the chyldren. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde propoſition (which is, that the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren are of the number of the faythfull) is knowen well ynough.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10054:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">iii.</note> The thyrd argument is gathered vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fact of Peter, which is peculier, but yet in it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publike adminiſtraction of baptiſm is touched. He coulde not forbyd theym the water of baptiſme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had receyued the holy ghoſt, but ſealed them as the people of god. Ergo, he could not deny baptiſme vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children, ſyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had learned in the goſpel y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the chyldren be of god, &amp; that the kyngdom of heauen is theyrs. Who woulde thynke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any man is mete for the kyngdom of heauen, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſpiryt?</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">iiii.</note> We do make &amp; gather the fourth argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon the ſtrength &amp; force of circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſion, in ſtede wherof, baptiſme is in the church of Chriſt. As many as were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of god, did afore al thinges, labour &amp; endeuour the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, to circumciſe theyr childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ioſu. v. Exo. iiii. The Apoſtles were the moſt faithfull miniſters of god: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did not thei omit or leaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was not brought in, in ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, Ergo, thei did baptiſe, not onli the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were of age, but alſo children.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">v.</note> Fyftely we do thus reaſon vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vſe &amp; cuſtome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſltes. The Apoſtles of Chriſt did dyrecte al their doinges to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniencie &amp; example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
                  <p>This we do proue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. iiii. Euangeliſts,
<pb facs="tcp:10054:34"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10054:34"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10054:35"/> the Actes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles, by the epiſtles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, Rom. xv. ii. Cor. ii. ii. Tim. iii. ii. Peter .i. chap. Ergo, they dyd order bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme after the Analogie and figure of the old Teſtament. The going through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> red ſea,<note place="margin">The go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge thorough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> read ſea, is a figure of baptiſm</note> was a type &amp; figure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was to come .i. Cor. x. cha. Children were in the fygure (for bothe men and women went through with theyr children) Ergo the apoſtles dyd not denie baptiſme vnto the children. The cuſtome &amp; maner of the ſcripture (whiche cuſtome and maner is vſed almoſt emong al nations) is not to reherce by name, women &amp; children, and yet neuertheleſſe it doth include them, for in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the father of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> famylie, or of the good man of the houſe, al hys whole famylie is comprehended, as in the chiefe or head. Yf thys were not, women ſhuld be in no ſmall ieoperdy, yf therfore they were not of god, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be not cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumciſed. Al theſe thynges are done, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes &amp; helpe of a figure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is called Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necdoche. The ſixte argument ſhalbe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manifeſt and expreſſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies of the apoſtles. The apoſtles did bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſe al whol houſholds and famylies, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go they did baptyſe children alſo, for the children are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> number of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> famylie or
<pb facs="tcp:10054:35"/> houſholde. Thys we do proue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xvii of Gene. For Abraham doth circumciſe al the male children y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were in his houſe. For he vnderſtode y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promys of god, that ſaith. I ſhal be thy god, &amp; the god of thy ſede. Likewyſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new Teſtament, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the goodman of the houſe, had herd &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell, that is to ſaie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god was his god, &amp; the god of his ſede alſo, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all them that were in his houſe bothe greate and ſmall, to be baptized. Thus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles dyd baptize hole houſholds and famylies. That the children do perteyne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers houſholde &amp; famylie, it is plaine &amp; manifeſt by the .xii. of Exodus &amp; ii. of the Actes: this do I inculcat &amp; beate the oftener into mens heades, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſe the Anabaptiſtes to be at this poynt that they do exclude y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mylie &amp; houſhold. for they can not denye but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole houſholds were baptized by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles. But who doth not ſe, that this cometh of mere contention? For though they could proue that there were no chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren at all in the famylies &amp; houſholdes, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles dyd baptiſe, yet had they not proued that al families or houſholds were, or be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wherfore we do make againe our argument after this ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:10054:36"/> The Apoſtles baptized al wholl houſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, ergo, thei did baptiſe children, ſyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> princypal &amp; chief part of the familie &amp; houſhold. But let vs put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there were no children in thoſe families &amp; houſholds, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Apoſtles dyd baptiſe, yet do they perteine &amp; belong to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, &amp; are rekened in it, and yf there had bene any, they wolde haue baptized the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For they did baptiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl houſholde. The fault then ſhuld not haue ben in the Apoſtles nor in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei were not baptized: but this had bene the cauſe that they had bene baptized, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there were none: For if they had had children they would haue baptyzed them.</p>
                  <p>Seuenthlye, we do gather by the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoryes &amp; chronicles that the baptiſme of children hath continued euer ſens the apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles time, vnto this time. Origene, which in the yeare of our ſaluation .c.c. &amp; .xii. did liue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Alexandria, doth in his v. boke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did wryt vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> epiſtle to the Romaines, teſtifie and witneſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath receaued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of children, from, or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles. After this time, about the yeare of oure Lorde. C.C.lv. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy man Cipryan was, he doth proue, &amp; that with no ſmall argumentes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in the .iii. boke of hys Epiſtles, and
<pb facs="tcp:10054:36"/> viii. epiſtle <hi>Adfidum,</hi> To fidus. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere of our lord .c.c.c.xx. Lactantius did wryte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iiii. boke of his diuyne Inſttucion, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſm was come in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtede of circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whereby all natyons ſhould be gathered vnto the faith, &amp; into the church.<note place="margin">Lactanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in hys iiii. boke, &amp; iiii. chapte</note> Hierome which did lyue about the yere of our lord c.c.c. &amp; lxx. doth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> playn &amp; expreſſe ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſm of children to Leta and agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pelagians. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſelf tyme and .xl. yeares after. Auguſtyn, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng a man endued with great holyneſſe of lyfe, with exceading great erudition &amp; learnyng, &amp; with a ſharpe and exacte iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement did teche in Aphrica. This man writeth many thinges of baptiſm againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Donatiſtes, to Marcellinus &amp; Petilia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus, where he doth manifeſtely ſaye,<note place="margin">Chryſte coulde not be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſm was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the lawe dyd regne tyll them.</note> that the church hath receiued the baptiſme of children, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles. I haue brought theſe thynges therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou mayſte ſee &amp; vnderſtand, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſme of children is no new inuention, &amp; that they whyche teche ſuche thinges do leane to no truth, but to plaine errour. For although chriſt was not baptized, tyll he was .xxx. yeares old, yet being an infant he was circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyght daye, that I ſhoulde in the meane ſeaſon let paſſe, that baptiſme was
<pb facs="tcp:10054:37"/> not yet inſtituted, which had hys begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of Ihon. But now we wyll ſtryke vp our ſayle clothes, and ſhewe how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kunninglye ye gather your argumentes, when ye do reaſon after this maner. We do not read that the apoſtles dyd baptiſe the chyldren of the faythfull: Ergo, they oughte not to be baptiſed. If we ſhoulde onelye goo by coniectures and reaſon, it is more lykelye, that the Apoſtles dyd baptyſe the infauntes then otherwyſe in the famylye, and houſholde of Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, of Lidia, of the keper of the priſon, &amp; of other, yf at leſte, there were any infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in thoſe famylyes and houſholdes,<note place="margin">Do not thynke good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that we goo a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fende vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrytten verytes.</note> which examples ye ſhall neuer be able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fute. There be many things done both by Chriſt and by the apoſtles, that neuer were written. Nor we can not make our argument after this maner: This thinge was not done. ergo, it may not lawfully be done. That we ſhuld graunt vnto you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the apoſtles did baptiſe no children, yet haue ye not proued therfore, that children ought not to be baptized. Again we may not to thys affyrmatyue. (The apoſtles dyd baptyſe them that were of age &amp; did beleue) inferre or bringe in, this negatiue (Ergo childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought not to be baptized)
<pb facs="tcp:10054:37"/> for we may neuer, neither in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophane nor yet in the holy ſcriptures, make oure argument, <hi>a facto ad ius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">To argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or reaſone a <hi>facto ad ius</hi> is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we go about to proue a thynge to be lawfull becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it was don afore, or elles to be vnlawfull becauſe it was not don afore</note> but then it is law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full to bringe the fact and dede for a law, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is proued that the dede was done rightfully.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>As I do hear the controuerſye is of the facte, and of the ryghte or lawfulnes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſaieſt truth if anye thinge be lawfull, as ſoone as thou haſt done it, thou haſt done well though that none of the apoſtles did it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the. Therfore baptiſme oughte not to be denyed vnto infantes, becauſe that we do not reade expreſſely, that the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did baptiſe infantes. Both becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they did baptiſe infants (as we haue proued &amp; ſhewed alreadye, and hereafter, if nede be, wil ſhew more large<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly) &amp; yet it was not writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; alſo becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no mans factes ought to be preiudicial vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, much leſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are left vndone. Therfore, if it were written any where w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> plain &amp; expreſſe words of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles after this maner: The apoſtles dyd not baptiſe infauntes, yet it ſhoulde not folowe that they oughte not too be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyzed: but we oughte too enquyre and ſearche, whether that they lefte it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, becauſe that it was notte lawfull,
<pb facs="tcp:10054:38"/> Chriſt did not baptiſe.<note place="margin">Chriſt did not baptiſ &amp; yet we ought to baptiſe.</note> Ihon. iiii. Ergo, af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter or according to your ſaying, we ought not to baptiſe at al. Who is ſo mad to ſay ſo? For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles did baptiſe &amp; that law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully. Ergo, If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles, did baptiſe law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully, though chriſt him ſilf did neuer bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe, we ſhal alſo lawfully baptiſe infants, though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles did not baptyſe. There is no diuerſitie at al, yea, we haue gotten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtaffe, ſyth that we haue Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> did not baptiſe, &amp; yet we ought to baptiſe, and ye onelye haue the apoſtles. Bring ye therfore any lawe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> forbiddeth to baptiſe children. We do not go about by theſe reaſons &amp; examples, as by ſome ſtrong foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to proue or ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptiſm of infantes (For we haue many other ſtrong arguments &amp; foundations) But we will ſhewe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye do both raſhely &amp; lyingly ſay, that the apoſtles dyd neuer baptiſe infantes or yong babes. For ye haue no teſtimonye of that thynge. And though ye had neuer ſo much, yet it ſhuld not folow therfore, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infantes ought not to be baptized: For vpon a thyng that is done, or left vndone, nothing can beſureli concluded, but onely vpon that, whyche is ſure by goddes worde to be lawful. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, we did bryng ſo many reaſons &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10054:38"/> examples to this intente, that we myght proue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is more likely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they dyd bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe chyldren than otherwiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou doeſt boſt much of foundations,<note place="margin">The chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are as wel of the people of god, by the ſtrength of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt as theyr pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes.</note> but thou bringeſt forth very lytle. I praie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, which be theſe ſtrong foundations.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue caſt thys foundation, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the children of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful are as wel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the church, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Children of god, as the parents &amp; that by the force and ſtrength of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys, as wel as they were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. Beſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, circumciſion (as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacramental meaning) was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thynge vnto them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> baptiſme was vnto vs. Dyd I not alredie both ſaye &amp; proue theſe things? Why ſayeſt thou then that I haue brought yet litle or nothing?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>MON.</speaker>
                  <p>Why doſt thou take all thinges out of the olde Teſtament.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>I know what the matter is, ye caſt away the olde Teſtament, for ye ſe that the baptiſme of chyldren may be proued &amp; defended by it Dyd not both Chriſt and his Apoſtles a alege y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old Teſtament, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo euer they wold proue and ſtrengthen their ſayings Or tell me now when Chriſt doth byd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes to ſerch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, doth he not ſend them to the old Teſtament?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM,</speaker>
                  <p>I do not denye that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
                  <p>Why do ye
<pb facs="tcp:10054:39"/> blame vs then, if we folowyng the exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of Chriſte, do ſtrengthen &amp; confirme our ſayings w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſcriptures of the olde Teſtament?<note place="margin">The newe Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; the olde are inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in an other</note> The new teſtament is inclu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded in the old, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old doth ſhadowe &amp; proue the new. If thou be ſufficyentlye perſwaded in this concluſion, let vs paſſe furth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>Certain thinges do pleaſe me wel, but that thou doeſt recken &amp; number the children in the familie and houſhold, I do not ſe it proued yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>Diddeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> neuer ſe then, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men are borne of men? &amp; that parents (I meane fathers and mothers) do nouriſh, kepe, &amp; brynge vp their chyldren? Haſte thou ſo caſte of all humayne reaſon, vnderſtandyng and affectyon? But yet in thys moſte plaine matter, I wyll bringe and alege the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures. Actes .ii. Chapter. We reade after thys maner: And all they that beleued, were together, or in one place, and had al thynges commen emonge theym. Here I doo aſke the, whether the faythefull hadde theyr chyldren with them, or not? If they hadde them, whye ſhoulde they not be then of theyr famylye and houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. If they had them not, whye do we not reade then, that the faythefull tooke thoughte, becauſe they myghte not haue
<pb facs="tcp:10054:39"/> theyr children wyth theym? Or was the ſpiryte that gouerned them ſo cruel, that it did teache them to put away their chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
                  <p>We wyll not ſay, that they had not theim wyth theym, or that they dyd not brynge theym vp, but that they were not in the famylye and houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde of Chriſte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
                  <p>Whome do ye comprehend then, vnder the name of famylye or houſholde?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SSMON.</speaker>
                  <p>Suche as be of that age alreadye, that they may know what the law is, &amp; what ſynne is. For he that wyll be baptyzed, muſte repente: ſythe that infauntes can not repente, they can not be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnder the name of the famylye, or houſholde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
                  <p>Whye doeſt thou ſtyll make vp a rope of ſande, haue we not proued alreadye before that, not onelye they that be of age, oughte too be baptyzed: But yeare ſoo ſtyffe necked that ye wyll in noo wyſe beleue, that a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye maye be baptyzed, onleſſe he maye repente of hys miſdedes. And by and by ye do conclude that, ergo, children ought not to be baptiſed. But in the meane ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, ye haue not yet ſhewed anye lawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> orbiddeth to baptyſe the chyldren. We (as we haue declared before alreadye)
<pb facs="tcp:10054:40"/> do knowe,<note place="margin">Iſaac. Agar. Iſmael.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iſaac being an infaunt was ſo of the familie &amp; houſhold of Abraham that he did cauſe his father to put awaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bond woman, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her childe. For Paul ſaith w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Moiſes: The ſonne of the bond woman ſhal not be heire, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my ſonne I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac, he was heyre, then w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out doubte he was of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> familie, for they that be not hei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, as ſeruantes &amp; fre men are of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. Exo. xii. We reade after thys maner: If ani ſtranger wil come to dwel emong you, &amp; kepe the paſſeouer of the lorde, let al his male children be circumciſed, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhal kepe it well. Why is it ſaid, al his male childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Doth this pertein onely to them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be of age? It is your part then to proue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they which receiue the ſeale of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of god, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religion of theyr parents, are not of the familye and houſholde of their parentes. But I wil bryng an oher teſtimonye. In the .xxi. of Acts, Luk writeth after this maner: And after certen daies, we departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thens &amp; they al brought vs on our way, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their wiues &amp; children. Were al theſe children of age? Or if they were not of age, were they not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> familie &amp; houſhold of theyr parents? What myracle, or what affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was it if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men did onely bring forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle on his way, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their wiues &amp; yong
<pb facs="tcp:10054:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> men? But this was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate affection, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fathers with their wiues, did beare &amp; draw their children w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, as in ſuche a buſines it is wont to be. Now, they dyd not draw w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, other mens, but their own childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ergo, they were of their fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>milie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>What though they pertain to theyr familie &amp; houſhold? Doth it folow therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wer baptized?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſhuld then Paul ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath baptized the houſhold of Stephana, which he had not baptized, if there were children in it, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had not admitted or receued? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Acts, it is ſaid. He was bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay) (the keper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> priſon) &amp; al his houſhold.<note place="margin">At the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gininge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythfull wer wont to folow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> example of Abraham and of his poſteritye.</note> Why wil ye not ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull wer wont to do as Abraham &amp; his poſteritie, which did cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe al their ſeruants, &amp; not only their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xii. of Exodus (as it is ſaid alredy before) al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> male childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the familie, are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to be circumciſed &amp; yet there no mention of faith, or of the knowlege of god (which thinges ought to be cared for aboue al thinges) is made there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſemeſt too me alwaies to leaue thoſe things, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> make agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. For in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> epiſtle to the Corin. Paule na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſuch a familye and houſhold, doth
<pb facs="tcp:10054:41"/> manifeſtly declare, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not infants &amp; yong babes, but ſuche as haue reaſon &amp; vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding, ought to be vnderſtanded. For he ſaith: ye know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Stephana, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are the firſt frutes of Achaia, &amp; haue giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to the ſeruice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaints be ye obedient to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke &amp; labour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them. Why do ye not ſpeake of ſuche a familie &amp; houſholde?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>We haue ſaid alredy, &amp; that often, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thys is a Sinecdochicall phraſe, or maner of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: ſuch as is .i. Cor. x.. Al our fathers were vnder the cloude, for infantes were alſo vnder the cloude: but no expreſſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion is made of them. Al went through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea, but the infants could not go through Thei went through then, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> went not tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row, but were born by them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> went tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. So there were ſome in the familye of Stephana, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleued firſt of al Achaia, there were alſo ſome of the congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> could not yet beleue in dede, for lack of age, nor giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to the miniſterye &amp; ſeruice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saints. Al wer baptized in Moſes: he ſpeketh al things of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to lay, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aunceters &amp; grandfathers who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> notwithſtandinge, we do ſo take, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were then children, are now called fathers by Paul. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of Iſrael was
<pb facs="tcp:10054:41"/> of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therefore, not onely they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were of age, were baptized in Moiſes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the infants. For if they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were then in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fants, were not baptized in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> going tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> red ſea, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paul ſaid not wel y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al were baptized in Moiſes. For they were alſo (as we haue ſaid afore) the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> came after.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
                  <p>This was a figure, what ſhalt thou then proue by it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>I am wel content. It was a fi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infants were then of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> family as wel of the earthly father, as of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, and were ſigned or ſealed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr ſacramentes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo now, they that are the children of the chriſtians, ſyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are the chyldren of god alſo, ought to vſe the ſacramente of the children of god. Thou canſt finde no ſtarting hole, to eſcape at. For ye do folyſhlye vpon factes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aumples, brynge in a negatiue: yea, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon neyther factes nor examples, that is to ſay, ye do vnwiſely make your argument, after this maner: Thys thing was done, as we maye proue both by te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtimonies &amp; examples: Ergo, that thinge oughte not to be done. For what other thing can ye alege for your ſelfs: but we do not read, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles did baptiſe in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fantes: ergo, they ought not to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.
<pb facs="tcp:10054:42"/> We do not ſo: but we might ſtay our ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues vpon facts &amp; examples (if ye woulde ſtand to) after this maner. The infantes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hebrues were al baptized vnder the cloud, &amp; in the ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, as well as ours. For Paul doth altogether proue there in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſaid place, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were no leſſe initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſacraments, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are our ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues. Firſt &amp; formeſte, then it foloweth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in Paules time,<note place="margin">The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had the ſame ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles were wont to baptiſe infants. Secondly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſoeuer denieth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth deprauate &amp; marre the ſentence of Paul. For what other thing doth he there, but make al things equal? and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are not aboue, or ſuperiours vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor they inferyours vnto vs? For he attributeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſacramentes vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue, &amp; the ſame vnto vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei had, as Colloſſ. ii. Now al thoſe auncient fathers could not haue bene baptized as wel as we, yf we be not al baptized w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our familie &amp; houſholdes. Them al therefore being baptized and made equall vnto vs it is manifeſt and plain, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as all their infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes were baptized in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> red ſea in Moiſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo in the apoſtles time, al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtians,<note place="margin">This fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necdoche is when eyther ſome whol thynge, is taken for parte of it, or part of it for the wholl, as ye ſhall herafter haue exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowghe.</note> were baptized in Chriſte. It is then Sinecdochically ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of Iſrael: They went al through the ſea,
<pb facs="tcp:10054:42"/> where as, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter or literally, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thorough, is applyed onely vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were in health, &amp; of age to go through their ſelfes. And al thei did eate one ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual meate, where as thei only did eate, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were ſpiritual, &amp; yet neuertheleſſe it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of al them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> did eat. In lyke maner, yf paul in this place had added this word (All) &amp; ſo had ſayd: All they of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Stephana haue geuen them ſelues to the miniſterie &amp; ſeruyce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaintes, yet by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force &amp; ſtrength of this figur Sinecdoche we ſhuld vnderſtand, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there were infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> familie and houſhold, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they, which had beleued alredie, had geuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord. For this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of this figure Synecdoche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when there is ſome wholl body, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath many partes, which in ſome thinge are lyke, &amp; in ſome thinge vnlyke, yf any thing is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl body, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame may be vnderſtanded of a ſingular part of it: Again, yf any thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge is ſpoken of any ſingular part, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame may lyke wyſe be vnderſtand of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl body. Learne ye this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſay, by familyar examples. All wholl Iurye went forthe vnto hym: Here ye ſe, that al Iury is put only for them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> went forth vnto hym, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther be to maner of Synecdoche, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one
<pb facs="tcp:10054:43"/> wherby y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which conteyneth any thyng, is taken for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which is conteyned, as the contrey of Iurye, for al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabitours: &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, wherby, it is ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours went forth, wher as parte only did go forth vnto him. Contrary wyſe in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaye.<note place="margin">The daughters of Syon.</note> iii. Becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the daughteres of Sy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, are waxen proude, there the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are parte of Syon. and yet they are taken for all the wholl people, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally for the prynces and rulers, whiche vngodly did riſe agaynſt the Lorde. Exo xvi. All the congregatyon dyd murmure againſt Moſes. But how did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children murmure, whyche knewe not what was done?<note place="margin">The ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptyſtes are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt in thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſerue to expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the letter which thei ſtycke to alwayes.</note> If they did not murmur &amp; grudge al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregation did not murmur: For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infants were of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregation. Nowe ſe, I praye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, what pratinge ſmatteres ye are, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye truſt moſt vpon, ye are moſt ſhamefully ignorant in. For ye ſtick to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter, but ye are ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth moſt chyefely ſerue to vnderſtand &amp; expound y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter. Tel I beſech y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it ſayd: Do not take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of thy Lorde god in vayne. Thou ſhalte not ſteale, &amp; ſuche like?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>To them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were of age, which are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, &amp; congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>Ergo, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges can not be ſaid vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:10054:43"/> thei not be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church &amp; people of God? God forbid: For Infantes were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god, &amp; fathers of naci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; peoples. Gene. xxv. It is plaine and manifeſte then, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what ſoeuer is ſpoken, to any wholl body or generalitie:<note place="margin">Marke ye this.</note> And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame generaletye there is ſome part, to whom y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is ſpoken, is not applied, yet notwithſtanding it is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, yea, though certain thing do pertain nothing vnto it. Agayne, if any thyng be ſpoken to part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> generality, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che not withſtandyng, doth not pertayne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parte: It perteyneth ſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl body, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it toucheth and admoniſheth only thoſe partes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maye be ſubiect vnto that, which is ſpoken. Thou art myne enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, O Iſrael. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is this ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Is not this ſpoken to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl poſteritye of Iſrael? But childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do not vnderſtand it. It foloweth not therfor, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei are not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enheritaunce or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peculier people. But though it is a parte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnderſtandeth not what is ſaid, yet neuertheles it pertei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whol body. In like maner, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſaieth: Go ye, teach al nations bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tizing them &amp;c. The apoſtles did teche as many as were able to receaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine, &amp; baptized as many, as were able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue baptiſm,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>Therfore I do thinke
<pb facs="tcp:10054:44"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infantes ought not to be baptized, ſyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt ſaith ſo expreſſely: Go thorough out al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl world, &amp; prech the goſpel, whoſoeuer ſhall beleue &amp; is baptized &amp;c. Going forth, teache ye all nations.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>This is the only refuge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye alwaies flee to, although Chriſt, had inſtituted bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm there, where as Ihon &amp; the apoſtles did both prech &amp; baptiſe long afore, when Chriſt was yet a lyue:<note place="margin">The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion was emonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles touchyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preching of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to the gentles.</note> There was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention emong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles, whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell ought to be preached to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gentyles, or not. Which contention did riſe partlie of a falſe concluſion &amp; coniecture, &amp; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely of a likelyhode. The falſe concluſion or coniectur was this: Chriſt is promiſed vnto vs, ergo he doth not perteyne or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gentyles. Who is ſo without vnderſtanding, which doth not perceaue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this can folow by no mean? The meſſias is promiſſed vnto vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be Iues, ergo, he doth nothing perteine to gentyles. For it maie be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is alſo promiſſed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles, which thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures do teſtefy in many places. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſelf maner do ye gather your argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but falſely: The wrytinges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles do teſtifye &amp; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they did baptiſe them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had both harde &amp; beleued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word: ergo, thei did not
<pb facs="tcp:10054:44"/> baptiſe infantes. For theſe .ii. ſentences mai both be true. The apoſtles did baptiſe them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleued: &amp;: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles did baptiſe infants. Ye do make an indefinite propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſityon, an excluſyue or negatiue propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, ye do make of a ſentence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> affyrmeth, a ſentence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtterly deneith. For both theſe are negatyues: No man ought to be baptized, onleſſe he doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, &amp;: Infants ought not to be baptized. Ye were not hetherto able to proue anye of them by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures. The lykelyhode wherby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles were moued to think, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the goſpel ought not to be preached, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gentyles, was thys: In their fyrſt miſſion &amp; ſending, they were forbiden to go into y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> waye of the gentyles: whyche word myght had cauſed them to contend &amp; ſtryue, and that ſtoutely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte was mynded to kepe him ſelfe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hebrewes onely. Yf ye had now any ſuch word, O lord god, ſo ye would triumphe agaynſte vs. Marke thou therfore. Theſe .ii. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundementes (Go ye &amp; teche all nations baptizing them: &amp;: Go through out all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl world, &amp; preach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel) were a diſpenſation &amp; an aboliſſhyng of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicte or prohibition (ye ſhal not go in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waie of the gentilles.) For they had
<pb facs="tcp:10054:45"/> alredy before both taught and baptyzed, which thyng eyther ye do not marke, or elles ye do diſſemble it craftely. He doth therfore open y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl prouynce of al the wholl world vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were afore inclu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded &amp; in a maner ſhut vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> borders of Iury. Theſe places the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ſet againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt,<note place="margin">Antithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis is a figure where by one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is ſet agaynſte the other.</note> as twoe Anttytheſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>The place y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou haſt aleged before out of the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Act, doth make greatli againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. For it ſhuld folow, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infantes had both ſolde &amp; diſtributed theyr goods, &amp; many other thinges myght be gathered ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
                  <p>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye gather your argument after this maner: Yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infantes be numbered emong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythfull: It folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they dyd ſel and diſtribute theyr goodes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they dyd praye &amp; breake bread, for they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beleued, dyd ſo. Who doth not ſee, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye expounde all thynges after the letter, &amp; yet ye doo not weyghe &amp; ponder it? The infantes are of the familie &amp; houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of their parentes, which thynge we haue proued ſufficienly before, whom ſith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye had rather to comprehend vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of houlſhold ſtuffe, then of the faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, ye do not only in this thing, moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly, but alſo moſt cruelly. It is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted in this figur Synecdoche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:10054:45"/> is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſaid of ſome whol body y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame be verified of al partes. For the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is no Sinecdoche: When y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, may be veryfied of al partes, it is no trope nor figur. But the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is a true ſinec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doche, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eyther ſome part is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl body, or elles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl bodi for part therof. As in Exo. xxiii. where it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: That al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> male kynde ſhal apeare before the Lord thriſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> year, here y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſeeſt thys word (All) Tell me now, were all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cradelles caried fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al Paleſtina thriſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare to Hieruſalem? If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſay eſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was ſo, ergo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infantes (according to thy reaſon) did .vii. dayes eate unlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uened bread, did ſowe fyeldes, did offer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt frutes. Which thyng ſyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they did not: it foloweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the male chyldren are not comprehended. If they were nott brought, then this is not true that all the male kind did thriſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> year apear befor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde: &amp; though at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt ſight, it ſemeth to haue a ſhew, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> male children are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre feaſtes, yet for al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, thei are onely bound by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe, that are of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may heare &amp; vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctryne, or offer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt frutes, or beare about branches of trees accordyng to the variety of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſtes &amp; faſhion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rightes
<pb facs="tcp:10054:46"/> As it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Deut .xxxi. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lecture or reading of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe: it apeareth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thoſe childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did come, which did alredi begyn to vnderſtand, what was red.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>What is this figure Sinecdoche, or from whens doth it come?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>IO.</speaker>
                  <p>Synecdoche, is compounded of Syn,<note place="margin">Wherof ſynecdoch commeth.</note> ek, and Decho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me. As yf a man ſhould ſaye: Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I do take an wholl bodye, I do vnderſtande ſome thinge a parte, or by it ſelfe of thoſe thinges, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are together comprehended in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame body. It maye in laten be called <hi>comprehenſio,</hi> howbeit it agreeth not all together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Greke word. But what do we ſtryue for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word? Tell me now, haue theſe things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue reaſoned vpon he therto, ſatiſfied the?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SI.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue nothing to ſay againſt ſo manifeſt ſcriptures. Nor it is not decent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man ſhuld repugne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth. I would that thou ſhuldeſt take mine obiections although, thei did procede from an ignoraunce perſon, which yet coueteth to be taught and inſtructed.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprynted at Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by Ihon Oſwen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNO. DO.</hi> 1551.</p>
            <p>☞ <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10054:46"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
